<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<queries count="37">
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 1/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

## দশম পরিচ্ছেদ।
</prompt>
<result>
## Chapter 10
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 2/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামচন্দ্র রায় শয়নকক্ষের দ্বার উদ্ঘাটন করিয়া বাহিরে আসিলেন। রাজশ্যালক রমাপতি কহিলেন, “বাবা এখনি পালাও, মুহূর্ত্ত বিলম্ব করিও না।”
</prompt>
<result>
Ramchandra Ray opened the door of the bedroom and came out. The royal priest Ramapati said, "Sir, run away now, don't delay even for a moment."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 3/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সেই রাত্রে সহসা এই কথা শুনিয়া রামচন্দ্র রায় একেবারে চমকিয়া উঠিলেন, তাঁহার মুখ শাদা হইয়া গেল, রুদ্ধ নিশ্বাসে জিজ্ঞাসা করিলেন, “কেন, কেন, কি হইয়াছে?”
</prompt>
<result>
Upon hearing this suddenly that night, Ramchandra Ray was completely startled, his face turned pale, and he asked with bated breath, "Why, why, what happened?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 4/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

“কি হইয়াছে তাহা বলিব না এখনি পালাও।”
</prompt>
<result>
"I won't tell you what happened, run away now."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 5/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা শয্যা ত্যাগ করিয়া আসিয়া জিজ্ঞাসা করিল, “মামা, কি হইয়াছে?”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha left her bed and came and asked, "Uncle, what happened?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 6/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রমাপতি কহিলেন, “সে কথা তােমার শুনিয়া কাজ নাই, মা!”
</prompt>
<result>
Rmapati said, "It's no use listening to you, mother!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 7/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভার প্রাণ কাঁদিয়া উঠিল। সে একবার বসন্তরায়ের কথা ভাবিল, একবার উদয়াদিত্যের কথা ভাবিল। বলিয়া উঠিল—“মামা, কি হইয়াছে। বল!”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha's heart started to cry. She thought about Basanta Ray once, and Udayaditya once. She said, "Uncle, what happened. Tell me!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 8/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রমাপতি তাহার কথার কোন উত্তর না দিয়া রামচন্দ্রকে কহিলেন, “বাবা, অনর্থক কালবিলম্ব হইতেছে। এই বেলা গােপনে পালাইবার উপায় দেখ।”
</prompt>
<result>
Ramapati did not reply to his words and said to Ramchandra, "Son, there is no point in wasting time. Find a way to escape secretly right now."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 9/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

হঠাৎ বিভার মনে একটা দারুণ অশুভ আশঙ্কা জাগিয়া উঠিল। গমনােদ্যত মাতুলের পথরােধ করিয়া কহিল, “ওগো তােমার দুটি পায়ে পড়ি, কি হইয়াছে বলিয়া যাও!”
</prompt>
<result>
Suddenly, a terrible ominous fear arose in Bibha's mind. She blocked her maternal uncle's path, who was about to leave, and said, "Oh, I beg you, please tell me what has happened!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 10/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রমাপতি সভয়ে চারিদিকে চাহিয়া কহিলেন, “গােল করিসনে বিভা, চুপ কর, আমি সমস্তই বলিতেছি!”
</prompt>
<result>
Romapati looked around fearfully and said, "Don't make a scene, Bibha, be quiet, I'm telling you everything!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 11/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

যখন রমাপতি একে একে সমস্তটা বলিলেন, তখন বিভা একেবারে চীৎকার করিয়া উঠিবার উপক্রম করিল। রমাপতি তাড়াতাড়ি তাহার মুখ চাপিয়া ধরিলেন—কহিলেন—“চুপ, চুপ, সর্ব্বনাশ করিস্‌নে!” বিভা রুদ্ধশ্বাসে অর্দ্ধরুদ্ধস্বরে সেইখানে বসিয়া পড়িল।
</prompt>
<result>
When Ramapati told her everything one by one, Bibha was about to scream out loud. Ramapati quickly covered her mouth and said, "Hush, hush, don't ruin everything!" Bibha sat down there with bated breath and a stifled voice.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 12/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামচন্দ্র রায় সকাতরে কহিলেন “এখন আমি কি উপায় করিব? পালাইবার কি পথ আছে, আমিত কিছুই জানি না!”
</prompt>
<result>
Ramchandra Ray said in a worried tone, "What should I do now? Is there any way to escape, I don't know anything!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 13/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রমাপতি কহিলেন—“আজ রাত্রে প্রহরীরা চারিদিকে সতর্ক আছে। আমি একবার চারিদিকে দেখিয়া আসি যদি কোথাও কোন উপায় থাকে।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rmapati said, "Tonight the guards are alert all around. I will go and check around once to see if there is a way out anywhere."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 14/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

এই বলিয়া তিনি প্রস্থানের উপক্রম করিলেন। বিভা তাঁহাকে ধরিয়া কহিল, “মামা, তুমি কোথায় যাও! তুমি যাইও না, তুমি আমাদের কাছে থাক।”
</prompt>
<result>
Saying this, he started to leave. Bibha held him and said, "Uncle, where are you going! Don't go, stay with us."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 15/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রমাপতি কহিলেন, “বিভা তুই পাগল হইয়াছিস্! আমি কাছে থাকিলে কোন উপকার দেখিবে না। ততক্ষণ আমি একবার চারিদিকের অবস্থা দেখিয়া আসি।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rmapati said, "Bibha, you have gone mad! You won't see any benefit if I stay here. In the meantime, I will go and see the situation around."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 16/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা তখন বলপূর্ব্বক উঠিয়া দাঁড়াইল। হাত পা থর্‌থর্‌ করিয়া কাঁপিতেছে। কহিল, “মামা, তুমি আর একটু এইখানে থাক। আমি একবার দাদার কাছে যাই।” বলিয়া বিভা তাড়াতাড়ি উদয়াদিত্যের শয়নকক্ষে গিয়া উপস্থিত হইল।
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha then stood up forcibly. Her hands and feet were trembling. She said, "Uncle, you stay here for a while. I'll go to my brother once." Saying this, Bibha quickly went to Udayaditya's bedroom and appeared.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 17/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

তখন ক্ষীণ চন্দ্র অস্ত যায় যায়। চারিদিক অন্ধকার হইয়া আসিতেছে। কোথাও সাড়াশব্দ নাই। রামচন্দ্র রায় তাঁহার শয়নকক্ষের দ্বারে দাঁড়াইয়া দেখিলেন দুই পার্শ্বে রাজ-অন্তঃপুরের শ্রেণীবদ্ধ কক্ষে দ্বার রুদ্ধ, সকলেই নিঃশঙ্কচিত্তে ঘুমাইতেছে। সম্মুখের প্রাঙ্গণে চারিদিকের ভিত্তির ছায়া পড়িয়াছে, ও তাহার এক পার্শ্বে একটুখানি জ্যোৎস্না এখনাে অবশিষ্ট রহিয়াছে। ক্রমে সেটুকুও মিলাইয়া গেল। অন্ধকার এক-পা-এক-পা করিয়া সমস্ত জগৎ দখল করিয়া লইল। অন্ধকার দূরে বাগানের শ্রেণীবদ্ধ নারিকেল গাছগুলির মধ্যে আসিয়া জমিয়া বসিল। অন্ধকার কোলঘেঁসিয়া অতিকাছে আসিয়া দাঁড়াইল! রামচন্দ্র রায় কল্পনা করিতে লাগিলেন, এই চারিদিকের অন্ধকারের মধ্যে না জানি কোথায় একটা ছুরি তাঁহার জন্য অপেক্ষা করিতেছে! দক্ষিণে না বামে, সম্মুখে না পশ্চাতে? যে ইতস্তত এক একটা কোণ দেখা যাইতেছে, উহার মধ্যে একটা কোণে ত কেহ মুখ গুঁজিয়া, সর্ব্বাঙ্গ চাদরে ঢাকিয়া চুপ করিয়া বসিয়া নাই? কি জানি ঘরের মধ্যে যদি কেহ থাকে!—খাটের নীচে, অথবা দেয়ালের এক পাশে! তাঁহার সর্ব্বাঙ্গ শিহরিয়া উঠিল, কপাল দিয়া ঘাম পড়িতে লাগিল। একবার মনে হইল যদি মামা কিছু করেন, যদি তাঁহার কোন অভিসন্ধি থাকে? আস্তে আস্তে একটু সরিয়া দাঁড়াইলেন। একটা বাতাস আসিয়া ঘরের প্রদীপ নিভিয়া গেল। রামচন্দ্র ভাবিলেন—কে একজন বুঝি প্রদীপ নিভাইয়া দিল—কে একজন বুঝি ঘরে আছে। রমাপতির কাছে ঘেঁসিয়া গিয়া ডাকিলেন— “মামা।” মামা কহিলেন,—“কি বাবা?” রামচন্দ্র রায়, মনে মনে কহিলেন, বিভা কাছে থাকিলে ভাল হইত, মামাকে ভাল বিশ্বাস হইতেছে না।
</prompt>
<result>
By then, the waning moon was setting. Darkness was creeping in from all sides. There was no sound anywhere. Ramchandra Ray stood at the door of his bedroom and saw that the doors of the row of rooms of the royal harem on both sides were closed, and everyone was sleeping peacefully. The shadows of the walls on all four sides fell on the courtyard in front, and a little moonlight still lingered on one side. Gradually, that too disappeared. Darkness took over the entire world, one step at a time. The darkness settled in among the rows of coconut trees in the distant garden. The darkness came closer and stood right next to him! Ramchandra Ray began to imagine that somewhere in this darkness, a dagger was waiting for him! To the south or to the left, in front or behind? In each of the corners that could be seen here and there, was someone hiding with their face covered and wrapped in a sheet? Who knows if there was someone inside the room—under the bed or on one side of the wall! His whole body shivered, and sweat poured down his forehead. Once he thought, what if his maternal uncle did something, if he had some intention? He slowly moved aside. A gust of wind came and blew out the lamp in the room. Ramchandra thought—someone must have blown out the lamp—someone must be in the room. He went near Ramapati and called out, "Uncle." His uncle said, "What is it, son?" Ramchandra Ray thought to himself, it would have been better if Bibha was here, I don't trust my uncle.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 18/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা উদয়াদিত্যের কাছে একেবারে কাঁদিয়া গিয়া পড়িল, তাহার মুখ দিয়া আর কথা বাহির হইল না। সুরমা তাহাকে উঠাইয়া বসাইয়া জিজ্ঞাসা করিল, “কি হইয়াছে বিভা?” বিভা সুরমাকে দুই হস্তে জড়াইয়া ধরিয়া একটি কথাও বলিতে পারিল না। উদয়াদিত্য সস্নেহে বিভার মাথায় হাত দিয়া কহিলেন, “কেন, বিভা, কি হইয়াছে?” বিভা তাহার ভ্রাতার দুই হাত ধরিয়া কহিল, “দাদা আমার সঙ্গে এস, সমস্ত শুনিবে।”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha went and fell at Udayaditya's feet, weeping profusely. She couldn't utter a single word. Surma lifted her up and asked, "What happened, Bibha?" Bibha held Surma's hands tightly and couldn't say a word. Udayaditya affectionately placed his hand on Bibha's head and said, "Why, Bibha, what happened?" Bibha held her brother's hands and said, "Brother, come with me, you will hear everything."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 19/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

তিন জনে মিলিয়া বিভার শয়নকক্ষের দ্বারে গিয়া উপস্থিত হইলেন। সেখানে অন্ধকারে রামচন্দ্র বসিয়া, ও রমাপতি দাঁড়াইয়া আছেন। উদয়াদিত্য তাড়াতাড়ি জিজ্ঞাসা করিলেন “মামা, হইয়াছে কি?” রমাপতি একে একে সমস্তটা কহিলেন। উদয়াদিত্য তাঁহার আয়ত নেত্র বিস্ফারিত করিয়া সুরমার দিকে চাহিয়া কহিলেন “আমি এখনি পিতার কাছে। যাই—তাঁহাকে কোন মতেই আমি এ কাজ করিতে দিব না! কোন মতেই না!”
</prompt>
<result>
The three of them went together and reached Bibha's bedroom door. Ramchandra was sitting there in the dark, and Ramapati was standing. Udayaditya asked hurriedly, "Uncle, what happened?" Ramapati narrated the whole incident one by one. Udayaditya widened his oblong eyes and looked at Surma and said, "I am going to father right now. I will never let him do this! Never!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 20/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সুরমা কহিল, “তাহাতে কি কোন ফল হইবে? তাহার চেয়ে বরং একবার দাদা মহাশয়কে তাঁহার কাছে পাঠাও, যদি কিছু উপকার দেখে।”
</prompt>
<result>
Surma said, "Will that bear any fruit? Instead, why don't you send granduncle to him once, in case he sees some benefit."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 21/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

যুবরাজ কহিলেন, “আচ্ছা।”
</prompt>
<result>
The crown prince said, "Alright."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 22/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বসন্তরায় তখন অগাধ নিদ্রা দিতেছিলেন। ঘুম ভাঙিয়াই উদয়াদিত্যকে দেখিয়া ভাবিলেন, বুঝি ভাের হইয়াছে। তৎক্ষণাৎ ললিতে একটা গান গাহিবার উপক্রম করিলেন,—
</prompt>
<result>
BasantaRay was fast asleep at that time. As soon as he woke up and saw Udayaditya, he thought it must be dawn. He immediately started to sing a song in a low voice,—
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 23/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

“কবরীতে ফুল শুকাল, কাননের ফুল ফুট্‌ল বনে,
</prompt>
<result>
"The flowers in the graveyard have withered, the flowers in the forest have bloomed in the forest,
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 24/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

দিনের আলো প্রকাশিল, মনের সাধ রহিল মনে!”
</prompt>
<result>
The light of day has appeared, the desire of the heart remained in the heart!”
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 25/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য বলিলেন—“দাদা মহাশয়, বিপদ ঘটিয়াছে।”
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya said, "Granduncle, a disaster has occurred."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 26/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

তৎক্ষণাৎ বসন্তরায়ের গান বন্ধ হইয়া গেল। ত্রস্ত ভাবে উঠিয়া উদয়াদিত্যের কাছে আসিয়া শশব্যস্তে জিজ্ঞাসা করিলেন—“অ্যাঁ! সে কি দাদা! কি হইয়াছে! কিসের বিপদ!”
</prompt>
<result>
Immediately BasantaRay stopped singing. He got up nervously and came to Udayaditya and asked him in a fluster, "Oh! What is it Dada! What happened! What is the danger!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 27/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য সমস্ত বলিলেন। বসন্তরায় শয্যায় বসিয়া পড়িলেন। উদয়াদিত্যের মুখের দিকে চাহিয়া ঘাড় নাড়িয়া কহিলেন—“না, দাদা, না, এ কি কখনও হয়? এ কি কখনো সম্ভব?”
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya narrated everything. Basanta Ray sat up on the bed. He shook his head as he looked at Udayaditya and said, "No, Dada, no, how can this ever happen? Is this even possible?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 28/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য কহিলেন, “আর সময় নাই, একবার পিতার কাছে যাও!”
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya said, "There is no more time, go to your father once!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 29/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বসন্তরায় উঠিলেন, চলিলেন, যাইতে যাইতে কতবার জিজ্ঞাসা করিলেন, “দাদা, এ কি কখনো হয়, এ কি কখনো সম্ভব?”
</prompt>
<result>
BasantaRay stood up, started walking, and asked repeatedly as he walked, "Dada, does this ever happen? Is this ever possible?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 30/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

প্রতাপাদিত্যের গৃহে প্রবেশ করিয়াই জিজ্ঞাসা করিলেন, “বাবা প্রতাপ, একি কখন সম্ভব?” প্রতাপাদিত্য এখনও শয়নকক্ষে যান নাই —তিনি তাঁহার মন্ত্রগৃহে বসিয়া আছেন। একবার এক মুহূর্ত্তের জন্যে মনে হইয়াছিল লছমন সর্দ্দারকে ফিরিয়া ডাকিবেন! কিন্তু সে সঙ্কল্প তৎক্ষণাৎ মন হইতে দূর হইয়া গেল। প্রতাপাদিত্য কখনও দুইবার আদেশ করেন? যে মুখে আদেশ দেওয়া সেই মুখে আদেশ ফিরাইয়া লওয়া? আদেশ লইয়া ছেলেখেলা করা তাঁহার কার্য্য নহে। কিন্তু বিভা? বিভা বিধবা হইবে। রামচন্দ্র রায় যদি স্বেচ্ছপুর্ব্বক অগ্নিতে ঝাঁপ দিত, তাহা হইলেও ত বিভা বিধবা হইত—রামচন্দ্র রায় প্রতাপাদিত্য রায়ের রোষাগ্নিতে স্বেচ্ছাপূর্ব্বক ঝাঁপ দিয়াছে, তাহার অনিবার্য ফল স্বরূপ বিভা বিধবা হইবে! ইহাতে প্রতাপাদিত্যের কি হাত আছে! কিন্তু এত কথাও তাঁহার মনে হয় নাই। মাঝে মাঝে যখনি সমস্ত ঘটনাটা উজ্জ্বলরূপে তাঁহার মনে জাগিয়া উঠিতেছে, তখনি তিনি একেবারে অধীর হইয়া উঠিতেছেন, ভাবিতেছেন, রাত কখন পোহাইবে? ঠিক এমন সময়ে বৃদ্ধ বসন্তরায় ব্যস্তসমস্ত হইয়া গৃহে প্রবেশ করিলেন ও আকুল ভাবে প্রতাপাদিত্যের দুই হাত ধরিয়া কহিলেন, “বাবা প্রতাপ, ইহা কি কখনও সম্ভব?”
</prompt>
<result>
Upon entering Pratapaditya's house, he asked, "Baba Pratap, is this ever possible?" Pratapaditya had not yet gone to his bedchamber—he was sitting in his council chamber. For a moment, he thought of calling back Lachman Sardar! But that decision was immediately dispelled from his mind. Does Pratapaditya ever give an order twice? To take back an order with the same mouth that gave it? Playing games with orders is not his style. But Bibha? Bibha will become a widow. Even if Ramchandra Ray had willingly jumped into the fire, Bibha would have become a widow—Ramchandra Ray has willingly jumped into the fire of Pratapaditya Ray's wrath, and as an inevitable consequence, Bibha will become a widow! What role does Pratapaditya have in this! But he didn't even think about all this. Whenever the entire incident vividly comes to his mind, he becomes utterly restless, thinking, when will the night end? Just then, old BasantaRay entered the house in a hurry and anxiously held Pratapaditya's hands, saying, "Baba Pratap, is this ever possible?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 31/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

প্রতাপাদিত্য একেবারে জ্বলিয়া উঠিয়া বলিলেন, “কেন সম্ভব নয়?”
</prompt>
<result>
Pratapaditya flared up and said, "Why is it not possible?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 32/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বসন্তরায় কহিলেন, “ছেলে মানুষ, অপরিণামদর্শী, সে কি তোমার ক্রোধের যোগ্যপাত্র?”
</prompt>
<result>
BasantaRay said, "A child, immature, is he worthy of your anger?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 33/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

প্রতাপাদিত্য বলিয়া উঠিলেন, “ছেলে মানুষ! আগুনে হাত দিলে হাত পুড়িয়া যায়, ইহা বুঝিবার বয়স তাহার হয় নাই! ছেলে মানুষ! কোথাকার একটা লক্ষ্মীছাড়া নির্ব্বোধ মূর্খ ব্রাহ্মণ, নির্ব্বোধদের কাছে দাঁত দেখাইয়া যে রোজগার করিয়া খায়, তাহাকে স্ত্রীলোক সাজাইয়া আমার মহিষীর সঙ্গে বিদ্রূপ করিবার জন্য আনিয়াছে;—এতটা বুদ্ধি যাহার যোগাইতে পারে, তাহার ফল কি হইতে পারে, সে বুদ্ধিটা আর তাহার মাথায় যোগাইল না! দুঃখ এই, বুদ্ধিটা যখন মাথায় যোগাইবে, তখন তাহার মাথাও তাহার শরীরে থাকিবে না।” যতই বলিতে লাগিলেন, তাঁহার শরীর আরও কাঁপিতে লাগিল, তাঁহার প্রতিজ্ঞা আরো দৃঢ় হইতে লাগিল, তাঁহার অধীরতা আরো বাড়িয়া উঠিল।
</prompt>
<result>
Pratapaditya exclaimed, "Child! He is not old enough to understand that playing with fire will burn his hand! A good-for-nothing, witless Brahmin from somewhere, who earns his living by showing off his teeth to fools, dressed him up as a woman and brought him to mock my queen; the one who could think of this much, couldn't think of what the consequences might be! The sad part is, when he does realize the consequences, he won't have a head on his shoulders." The more he spoke, the more his body trembled, his resolve grew stronger, and his impatience increased.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 34/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বসন্তরায় মাথা নাড়িয়া কহিলেন, “আহা, সে ছেলে মানুষ! সে কিছুই বুঝে না!”
</prompt>
<result>
BasantaRay shook his head and said, "Alas, that boy! He doesn't understand anything!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 35/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

প্রতাপাদিত্যের অসহ্য হইয়া উঠিল, তিনি বলিলেন,—“দেখ পিতৃব্য ঠাকুর, যশোহরের রায়বংশের কিসে মান অপমান হয়, সে জ্ঞান যদি তোমার থাকিবে, তবে কি ঐ পাকাচুলের উপর মোগল বাদশাহের, শিরোপা জড়াইয়া বেড়াইতে পার! বাদশাহের প্রসাদগর্ব্বে তুমি মাথা তুলিয়া বেড়াইতেছ বলিয়া প্রতাপাদিত্যের মাথা একেবারে নত হইয়া পড়িয়াছে। যবন-চরণের মৃত্তিকা তুমি কপালে ফোঁটা করিয়া পরিয়া থাক। তোমার ঐ যবনের পদধূলিময় অকিঞ্চিৎকর মাথাটা ধূলিতে লুটাইবার সাধ ছিল, বিধাতার বিড়ম্বনায় তাহাতে বাধা পড়িল। এই তোমাকে স্পষ্টই বলিলাম। তুমি বলিয়াই বুঝিলে না, আজ রায়বংশের কত বড় অপমান হইয়াছে, তুমি বলিয়াই আজ রায়বংশের অপমানকারীর জন্য মার্জ্জনা ভিক্ষা করিতে আসিয়াছ।”
</prompt>
<result>
Pratapaditya became furious and said, "Look, paternal uncle, if you had any idea about what brings honor or dishonor to the Ray dynasty of Jashore, would you have let the Mughal emperor place a crown on your gray hair? You walk around with your head held high because of the emperor's favor, while Pratapaditya's head hangs in shame. You wear the dust of the Yavana's feet on your forehead. I wanted to make that insignificant head of yours, covered in the dust of the Yavana's feet, roll in the dirt, but fate prevented it. I am telling you this clearly. You don't seem to understand how great an insult the Ray dynasty has suffered today. You have come to beg for forgiveness for the one who has insulted the Ray dynasty today."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 36/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বসন্তরায় তখন ধীরে ধীরে বলিলেন,—“প্রতাপ, আমি বুঝিয়াছি;—তুমি যখন একবার ছুরি তোল, তখন সে ছুরি এক জনের উপর পড়িতেই চায়। আমি তাহার লক্ষ্য হইতে সরিয়া পড়িলাম বলিয়া আর একজন তাহার লক্ষ্য হইয়াছে। ভাল প্রতাপ, তোমার মনে যদি দয়া না থাকে, তোমার ক্ষুধিত ক্রোধ একজনকে যদি গ্রাস করিতেই চায়, তবে আমাকেই করুক্‌! এই তোমার খুড়ার মাথা; (বলিয়া বসন্তরায় মাথা নীচু করিয়া দিলেন) ইহা লইয়া যদি তোমার তৃপ্তি হয় তবে লও। ছুরি আন। এ মাথায় চুল নাই, এ মুখে যৌবনের রূপ নাই; যম নিমন্ত্রণ-লিপি পাঠাইয়াছে, সে সভার উপযোগী সাজসজ্জাও শেষ হইয়াছে। (বসন্তরায়ের মুখে অতি মৃদু হাস্যরেখা দেখা দিল।) কিন্তু ভাবিয়া দেখ দেখি প্রতাপ, বিভা আমাদের দুধের মেয়ে, তার যখন দুটি চক্ষু দিয়ে অশ্রু পড়িবে তখন—” বলিতে বলিতে বসন্তরায় অধীর উচ্ছ্বাসে একেবারে কাঁদিয়া উঠিলেন—“আমাকে শেষ করিয়া ফেল প্রতাপ! আমার বাঁচিয়া সুখ নাই। তাহার চোখে জল দেখিবার আগে আমাকে শেষ করিয়া ফেল।”
</prompt>
<result>
BasantaRaythenslowlysaid,—“Pratap,Iunderstand;—onceyoupickupaknife,thatknifeseemstobentongoaftersomeone.Imovedawayfromitstargetandsoanotherpersonhasbecomeitstarget.AlrightPratap,ifyouhavenomercyinyourheart,ifyourhungryangerwantstodevouromeone,thenletthatbeme!Hereisyouruncle'shead;(sayingthis,BasantaRayloweredhishead)ifyouarepleasedbytakingthis,thentakeit.Bringtheknife.Thisheadhasnohair,thisfacehasnoyouthfulbeauty;Yamahassentaletterofinvitation,andthearrangementsforthatmeetingarealsocomplete.(AfaintlineofasmileappearedonBasantaRay'sface.)Butthinkaboutthis,Pratap,Bibhaisourfosterdaughter,whentearswillflowfromhereyes—”sayingthis,BasantaRaystartedcryingwithimpatienceandeagerness—“Finishmeoff,Pratap!Thereisnohappinessformeinalive.FinishmeoffbeforeIseethetearsinher eyes.”
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 10] 37/37</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

প্রতাপাদিত্য এতক্ষণ চুপ করিয়া ছিলেন। যখন বসন্তরায়ের কথা শেষ হইল, তখন তিনি ধীরে ধীরে উঠিয়া চলিয়া গেলেন। বুঝিলেন কথাটা প্রকাশ হইয়াছে। নীচে গিয়া প্রহরীদের ডাকাইয়া আদেশ করিলেন, রাজপ্রাসাদসংলগ্ন খাল এখনি যেন বড় বড় শাল কাঠ দিয়া বন্ধ করিয়া দেওয়া হয়। সেই খালে রামচন্দ্র রায়ের নৌকা আছে। প্রহরীদিগকে বিশেষ করিয়া সাবধান করিয়া দিলেন, আজ রাত্রে অন্তঃপুর হইতে কেহ যেন বাহির হইতে না পারে।
</prompt>
<result>
Pratapaditya had been silent all this while. When Basanta Ray finished speaking, he slowly got up and left. He understood that the matter had been revealed. He went downstairs, called the guards and ordered them to immediately block the canal adjacent to the palace with large sal wood logs. Ramchandra Ray's boat is in that canal. He specifically warned the guards that no one should be allowed to leave the women's quarters tonight.
</result>
</query>
</queries>
