<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<queries count="40">
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 1/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

## ত্রয়ােদশ পরিচ্ছেদ।
</prompt>
<result>
## Chapter 13.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 2/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বসন্তরায় উদয়াদিত্যের ঘরে আসিয়া কহিলেন, “দাদা তাের সঙ্গে আর দেখা হইবে না।” বলিয়া উদয়াদিত্যকে বৃদ্ধ দুই হাতে জড়াইয়া ধরিলেন।
</prompt>
<result>
BasantaRay came to Udayaditya's room and said, "Brother, I won't be able to see you again." Saying this, the old man held Udayaditya tightly with both hands.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 3/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য বসন্তরায়ের হাত ধরিয়া কহিলেন, “কেন দাদামহাশয়?”
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya held BasantaRay's hand and said, "Why, granduncle?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 4/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বসন্তরায় সমস্ত বলিলেন। কাঁদিয়া কহিলেন, “ভাই, তােকে আমি ভালবাসি বলিয়াই তাের এত দুঃখ। তা, তুই যদি সুখে থাকিস্ ত এক’টা দিন আমি একরকম কাটাইয়া দিব।”
</prompt>
<result>
BasantaRay told everything. He said while crying, "Brother, I love you that's why you are in so much pain. But if you are happy, then I will somehow manage to survive."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 5/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য মাথা নাড়িয়া কহিলেন, “না, তাহা কখনই হইবে না। তােমাতে আমাতে দেখা হইবেই। তাহাতে কেহ বাধা দিতে পারিবে না। তুমি গেলে দাদামহাশয়, আমি আর বাঁচিব না।”
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya shook his head and said, "No, that will never happen. We will meet for sure. No one can stop us. If you go, granduncle, I will not be able to live anymore."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 6/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বসন্তরায় ব্যাকুল হইয়া কহিলেন, “প্রতাপ আমাকে বধ করিল না, তােকে আমার কাছ হইতে কাড়িয়া লইল। দাদা, আমি যখন চলিয়া যাইব, আমার পানে ফিরিয়া চাহিস্‌নে, মনে করিস্‌ বসন্তরায় মরিয়া গেল!”
</prompt>
<result>
BasantaRay said anxiously, "Pratap did not kill me, he snatched you away from me. Brother, when I leave, don't look back at me, just think that BasantaRay is dead!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 7/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য শয়নকক্ষে সুরমার নিকটে গেলেন। বসন্তরায় বিভার কাছে গিয়া বিভার চিবুক ধরিয়া কহিলেন, “বিভা দিদি আমার, একবার ওঠ্! বুড়ার এই মাথাটায় একবার ঐ হাত বুলাইয়া দে।” বিভা উঠিয়া বসিয়া দাদা মহাশয়ের মাথা লইয়া পাকা চুল তুলিয়া দিতে লাগিল।
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya went near Surma in the bedroom. BasantaRay went near Bibha, held her chin and said, "Sister Bibha, please get up! Run your hand over this old man's head once." Bibha got up and sat down, took her grandfather's head and started combing his gray hair.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 8/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য সুরমাকে সমস্ত কহিলেন ও বলিলেন,—“সুরমা, পৃথিবীতে আমার যাহা কিছু অবশিষ্ট আছে তাহাই কাড়িয়া লইবার জন্য যেন একটা যড়যন্ত্র চলিতেছে।” সুরমার হাত ধরিয়া কহিলেন—“সুরমা, তােমাকে যদি কেহ আমার কাছ হইতে ছিনিয়া লইয়া যায়?”
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya told Surma everything and said, "Surma, it seems like there is a conspiracy going on to snatch away everything that I have left in this world." Holding Surma's hand, he said, "Surma, what if someone takes you away from me?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 9/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সুরমা দৃঢ়ভাবে উদয়াদিত্যকে, আলিঙ্গন করিয়া দৃঢ়স্বরে কহিল, “সে যম পারে, আর কেহ পারে না।”
</prompt>
<result>
Surma firmly embraced Udayaditya and said in a determined voice, "If Yama, the god of death, can do it, then no one else can."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 10/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সুরমার মনেও অনেকক্ষণ ধরিয়া সেইরূপ একটা আশঙ্কা জন্মিতেছে। সে যেন দেখিতে পাইতেছে একটা কঠোর হস্ত তাহার উদয়াদিত্যকে তাহার কাছ হইতে সরাইয়া দিবার জন্য অগ্রসর হইতেছে। সে মনে মনে উদয়াদিত্যকে প্রাণপণে আলিঙ্গন করিয়া ধরিল, মনে মনে কহিল, “আমি ছাড়িব না, আমাকে কেহ ছাড়াইতে পারিবে না।”
</prompt>
<result>
The same fear had been growing in Surma's mind for a long time. She seemed to see a cruel hand reaching out to take Udayaditya away from her. In her mind, she held Udayaditya tightly in her arms and said to herself, "I will not let go, no one can make me let go."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 11/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সুরমা আবার কহিল, “আমি অনেকক্ষণ হইতে ভাবিয়া রাখিয়াছি আমাকে তােমার কাছ হইতে কেহই লইতে পারিবে না।”
</prompt>
<result>
Surma said again, "I have been thinking for a long time that no one will be able to take me away from you."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 12/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সুরমা ঐ কথা বার বার করিয়া বলিল। সে মনের মধ্যে বল সঞ্চয় করিতে চায়, যে বলে সে উদয়াদিত্যকে দুই বাহু দিয়া এমন জড়াইয়া থাকিবে যে, কোন পার্থিব শক্তি তাহাদের বিচ্ছিন্ন করিতে পারিবে না। বার বার ঐ কথা বলিয়া মনকে সে বজ্রের বলে বাঁধিতেছে।
</prompt>
<result>
Surma repeated those words again and again. She wants to gather strength in her mind, with which she will embrace Udayaditya with both her arms in such a way that no worldly power will be able to separate them. By repeating those words again and again, she is binding her mind with the strength of a thunderbolt.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 13/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য সুরমার মুখের দিকে চাহিয়া নিশ্বাস ফেলিয়া কহিলেন সুরমা, দাদামহাশয়কে আর দেখিতে পাইব না!”
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya looked at Surma's face and sighed, saying, "Surma, I won't be able to see granduncle again!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 14/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সুরমা নিশ্বাস ফেলিল।
</prompt>
<result>
Surma sighed.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 15/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য কহিলেন, “আমি নিজের কষ্টের জন্য ভাবি না সুরমা,—কিন্তু দাদামহাশয়ের প্রাণে যে বড় বাজিবে। দেখি, বিধাতা আরো কি করেন। তাঁর আরও কি ইচ্ছা আছে!”
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya said, "I am not worried about my own suffering, Surma,—but I am very worried about my granduncle. Let's see what else the Creator does. What else does he want!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 16/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য বসন্তরায়ের কত গল্প করিলেন।
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya told many stories of Basanta Ray.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 17/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বসন্তরায় কোথায় কি কহিয়াছিলেন, কোথায় কি করিয়াছিলেন সমুদায় তাঁহার মনে পড়িতে লাগিল। বসন্তরায়ের করুণ হৃদয়ের কত ক্ষুদ্র ক্ষুদ্র কাজ, কত ক্ষুদ্র ক্ষুদ্র কথা, তাঁহার স্মৃতির ভাণ্ডারে ছােট ছােট রত্নের মত জমা করিয়া রাখিয়াছিলেন, তাহাই আজ একে একে সুরমার কাছে বাহির করিতে লাগিলেন।
</prompt>
<result>
BasantaRay's words and deeds started coming back to his mind. BasantaRay's compassionate heart, his numerous small acts of kindness, his countless little words, all these were stored in his memory like tiny jewels, and now he started sharing them one by one with Surma.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 18/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সুরমা কহিল, “আ—হা, দাদামহাশয়ের মত কি আর লােক আছে?”
</prompt>
<result>
Surma said, "Ah, is there anyone like granduncle?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 19/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সুরমা ও উদয়াদিত্য বিভার ঘরে গেলেন।
</prompt>
<result>
Surma and Udayaditya went to Bibha's room.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 20/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

তখন বিভা তাহার দাদা মহাশয়ের পাকা চুল তুলিতেছে, ও তিনি বসিয়া গান গাইতেছেন;—
</prompt>
<result>
At that time Bibha is combing her grandfather's gray hair, and he is sitting and singing a song;—
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 21/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

“ওরে, যেতে হবে, আর দেরী নাই,
</prompt>
<result>
"Oh, we have to go, no more delay,
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 22/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

পিছিয়ে প’ড়ে র’বি কত, সঙ্গীরা তাের গেল, সবাই।
</prompt>
<result>
How far behind Ravi has fallen, your companions have all gone.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 23/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

আয়রে ভবের খেলা সেরে, আঁধার করে এসেছেরে,
</prompt>
<result>
Oh, having finished the play of life, you have come, darkening everything,
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 24/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

(ওরে) পিছন ফিরে বারে বারে কাহার পানে চাহিস্‌রে ভাই।
</prompt>
<result>
(Hey) Why do you keep looking back again and again, brother?
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 25/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

খেল্‌তে এল ভবের নাটে, নতুন লোকে নতুন খেলা,
</prompt>
<result>
Came to play in the drama of life, new people, new play,
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 26/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

হেথা হতে আয়রে সরে, নইলে তােরে মার্‌বে ঢেলা,
</prompt>
<result>
Get out of here, or else I'll hit you with a stone.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 27/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

নামিয়ে দেরে প্রাণের বােঝা, আরেক দেশে চল্‌রে সোজা,
</prompt>
<result>
Having unloaded the burden of life, let's go straight to another country,
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 28/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

(সেথা) নতুন করে বাঁধবি বাসা, নতুন খেলা খেল্‌বি সে ঠাঁই।
</prompt>
<result>
(There) you will build a new house, you will play new games in that place.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 29/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্যকে দেখিয়া বসন্তরায় হাসিয়া কহিলেন, “দেখ ভাই, বিভা আমাকে ছাড়িতে চায় না। কি জানি আমাকে উহার কিসের আবশ্যক! এক কালে যে দুধ ছিল, বুড়া হইয়া সে ঘোল হইয়া উঠিয়াছে, তা, বিভা দুধের সাধ ঘােলে মিটাইতে চায় কেন? আমি যাব শুনিয়া বিভা কাঁদে! এমন আর কখন শুনিয়াছ? আমি ভাই, বিভার কান্না দেখিতে পারি না।” বলিয়া গাহিতে লাগিলেন,
</prompt>
<result>
Seeing Udayaditya, BasantaRay laughed and said, "Look brother, Bibha doesn't want to leave me. I don't know what she needs from me! Once there was milk, now that I have grown old, it has turned into buttermilk, so why does Bibha want to satisfy her craving for milk with buttermilk? Bibha cries when she hears that I am leaving! Have you ever heard of anything like this? Brother, I can't bear to see Bibha cry." Saying this, he started to sing,
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 30/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

“আমার যাবার সময় হল,
</prompt>
<result>
"It is time for me to go,
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 31/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

আমায় কেন রাখিস্ ধরে,
</prompt>
<result>
Why are you holding me back,
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 32/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

চোখের জলের বাঁধন দিয়ে
</prompt>
<result>
With the dam of tears
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 33/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বাঁধিস্‌নে আর মায়া-ডােরে।
</prompt>
<result>
I will not tie you with the strings of affection anymore.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 34/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ফুরিয়েছে জীবনের ছুটি;
</prompt>
<result>
The vacation of life is over;
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 35/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ফিরিয়ে নে তাের নয়ন দুটি,
</prompt>
<result>
Take back your two eyes,
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 36/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

নাম ধরে আর ডাকিস্‌নে ভাই,
</prompt>
<result>
You don't call me by my name anymore, brother,
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 37/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

যেতে হবে ত্বরা করে!”
</prompt>
<result>
"We have to go quickly!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 38/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

“ঐ দেখ, ঐ দেখ, বিভার রকম দেখ! দেখ্ বিভা, তুই যদি অমন করিয়া কাঁদবি ত—” বলিতে বলিতে বসন্তরায়ের আর কথা বাহির হইল না। তিনি বিভাকে শাসন করিতে গিয়া নিজেকে আর সামলাইতে পারিলেন না, তাড়াতাড়ি চোখের জল মুছিয়া হাসিয়া কহিলেন, “দাদা, ঐ দেখ ভাই সুরমা কাঁদিতেছে! এই বেলা ইহার প্রতিবিধান কর; নহিলে আমি সত্য সত্যই থাকিয়া যাইব; তােমার জায়গাটি দখল করিয়া বসিব। ঐ দুই হাতে পাকাচুল তােলাইব, ঐ কানের কাছে এই ভাঙা দাঁতের পাটির মধ্য হইতে ফিস্‌ফিস্ করিব, আর কানের অত কাছে গিয়া আর যদি কোন প্রকার অঘটন সংঘটন হয় তবে তাহার দায়ী আমি হইব না!”
</prompt>
<result>
"Look there, look there, see Bibha's antics! Look Bibha, if you cry like that then-" BasantaRay couldn't finish his sentence. He couldn't control himself while scolding Bibha, he quickly wiped away his tears and said with a smile, "Dada, look there, sister Surma is crying! Take care of her right now; otherwise, I will really stay here; I will occupy your place. I will tie up her long hair with both hands, I will whisper from the side of her broken teeth near her ears, and if any mishap happens because of going too close to her ears, then I won't be responsible!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 39/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বসন্তরায় দেখিলেন, কেহ কোন কথা কহিল না, তখন তিনি কাতর হইয়া তাঁহার সেতারটা তুলিয়া লইয়া ঝন্ ঝন্ করিয়া বিষম বেগে বাজাইতে সুরু করিলেন। কিন্তু বিভার চখের জল দেখিয়া তাঁহার সেতার বাজাইবার বড়ই ব্যাঘাত হইতে লাগিল, তাঁহার চোখ মাঝে মাঝে ঝাপ্‌সা হইয়া আসিতে লাগিল, মাঝে মাঝে বিভাকে এবং উপস্থিত সকলকে তিরস্কারচ্ছলে রাশ রাশ কথা বলিবার বাসনা হইতে লাগিল, কিন্তু আর কথা যােগাইল না, কণ্ঠ রুদ্ধ হইয়া আসিল, সেতার বন্ধ করিয়া নামাইয়া রাখিতে হইল। অবশেষে বিদায়ের সময় আসিল।
</prompt>
<result>
BasantaRaynoticedthatnoonesaidanything,sohebecameanxiousandpickeduphistamburaandstartedtoplayitveryfastwithajanglingnoise.However,seeingBibha'stears,itbecameverydifficultforhimtoplaythetambura,hiseyesstartedtoblurfromtimetotime,andhefeltlikeinsultingBibhaandeveryonepresent,buthecouldnotsayanything,histhroatchokedup,andhehadtostopandputawaythetambura.Finally,thetimeforfarewellcame.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 13] 40/40</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্যকে দীর্ঘকাল আলিঙ্গন করিয়া শেষ কথা এই বলিয়া গেলেন, “এই সেতার রাখিয়া গেলাম দাদা, আর সেতার বাজাইব না। সুরমা ভাই সুখে থাক; বিভা—” কথা শেষ হইল না, অশ্রু মুছিয়া পাল্কীতে উঠিলেন।
</prompt>
<result>
After embracing Udayaditya for a long time, she said these last words, "I am leaving this sitar with you, brother, I will not play the sitar anymore. May you live happily, brother Surma; Bibha—" She could not finish her sentence, she wiped her tears and got into the palanquin.
</result>
</query>
</queries>
