<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<queries count="28">
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 1/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

## চতুর্দ্দশ পরিচ্ছেদ।
</prompt>
<result>
## Chapter 14
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 2/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলার কুটীর যশোহরের এক প্রান্তে ছিল। সেইখানে বসিয়া সে মালা জপ করিতেছিল। এমন সময়ে শাকসব্‌জির চুব্‌ড়ি হাতে করিয়া রাজবাটীর দাসী মাতঙ্গিনী আসিয়া উপস্থিত হইল।
</prompt>
<result>
Mangala's hut was at one end of Jessore. She was sitting there and chanting the rosary. At that moment, Matangini, a maidservant of the royal palace, arrived with a basket of vegetables in her hand.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 3/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মাতঙ্গ কহিল, “আজ হাটে আসিয়াছিলাম, অমনি ভাবিলাম, অনেক দিন মঙ্গলাদিদিকে দেখি নাই, তা একবার দেখিয়া আসিগে। আজ ভাই অনেক কাজ আছে, অধিকক্ষণ থাকিতে পারিব না।” বলিয়া চুবড়ি রাখিয়া নিশ্চিন্ত ভাবে সেই খানে বসিল। “তা, দিদি তুমি ত সব জানই, সেই মিন্সে আমাকে বড় ভালবাসিত, ভাল এখনো বাসে, তবে আর একজন কা’র পরে তার মন গিয়াছে আমি টের পাইয়াছি—তা’ সেই মাগীটার ত্রিরাত্রির মধ্যে মরণ হয় এমন করিতে পার না?”
</prompt>
<result>
Matanga said, "I came to the market today and suddenly thought that I haven't seen elder sister Mangala for a long time, so let me go and see her. I have a lot of work today, I won't be able to stay for long." Saying this, he sat down there comfortably, leaning against a pillar. "Well, sister, you know everything, that meanie used to love me a lot, maybe she still does, but I have realized that her heart now belongs to someone else—so can't that witch kill him within three nights?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 4/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলার নিকট গরু হারানো হইতে স্বামী হারানো পর্য্যন্ত সকল-প্রকার দুর্ঘটনারই ঔষধ আছে, তা’ ছাড়া সে বশীকরণের এমন উপায় জানে যে, রাজবাটীর বড় বড় ভৃত্য মঙ্গলার কুটীরে কত গণ্ডা গণ্ডা গড়াগড়ি যায়! যে মাগীটার ত্রিরাত্রির মধ্যে মরণ হইলে মাতঙ্গিনী বাঁচে সে আর কেহ নহে স্বয়ং মঙ্গলা!
</prompt>
<result>
Mangala has remedies for all kinds of misfortunes, from losing a cow to losing a husband. Apart from that, she knows such methods of captivating people that the big servants of the royal palace roll around in heaps at Mangala's hut! The sorceress who can save Matangini if she dies within three nights is none other than Mangala herself!
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 5/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলা মনে মনে হাসিয়া কহিল, “সে মাগীর মরিবার জন্য বড় তাড়াতাড়ি পড়ে নাই, যমের কাজ বাড়াইয়া তবে সে মরিবে।” মঙ্গলা হাসিয়া প্রকাশ্যে কহিল, “তোমার মতন রূপসীকে ফেলিয়া আর কোথাও মন যায় এমন অরসিক আছে নাকি? তা’ নাতনী, তোদর ভাবনা নাই। তাহার মন তুমি ফিরিয়া পাইবে। তোমার চোখের মধ্যেই ঔষধ আছে, একটু বেশি করিয়া প্রয়োগ করিয়া দেখিও তাহাতেও যদি না হয়, তবে এই শিকড়টি তাহাকে পানের সঙ্গে খাওয়াইও।” বলিয়া এক শুক্‌ন শিকড় আনিয়া দিল।
</prompt>
<result>
Mangala thought to herself with a smile, "That witch is in no hurry to die, she will only die after increasing Yama's work." Mangala said openly with a smile, "Is there such an insensitive person who would leave a beauty like you and set his heart elsewhere? Don't worry, my granddaughter. You will win his heart back. You have the cure in your eyes, try using it a little more, and if that doesn't work, then feed him this root with betel leaf." Saying this, she brought a dried root.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 6/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলা মাতঙ্গিনীকে জিজ্ঞাসা করিল, “বলি রাজবাটীর খবর কি?”
</prompt>
<result>
Mangala asked Matangini, "Tell me, what is the news from the palace?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 7/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মাতঙ্গিনী হাত উল্টাইয়া কহিল, “সে সব কথায় আমাদের কাজ কি ভাই?”
</prompt>
<result>
Matangini turned her hand over and said, "What do we have to do with all that talk, brother?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 8/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলা কহিল, “ঠিক কথা। ঠিক কথা।”
</prompt>
<result>
Mangala said, "That's right. That's right."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 9/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলার যে এ বিষয়ে সহসা মতের এতটা ঐক্য হইয়া যাইবে, তাহা মাতঙ্গিনী আশা করে নাই। সে কিঞ্চিৎ ফাঁফরে পড়িয়া কহিল, “তা’ তোমাকে বলিতে দোষ নাই; তবে আজ আমার বড় সময় নাই; আর একদিন সমস্ত বলিব।” বলিয়া বসিয়া রহিল।
</prompt>
<result>
Matangini had not expected that Mangala would suddenly agree with her on this matter. She puffed up a little and said, "Well, I don't mind telling you, but I don't have much time today; I'll tell you everything another day." Saying this, she sat down.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 10/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলা কহিল—“তা বেশ, আর একদিন শুনা যাইবে।”
</prompt>
<result>
Mangala said - "That's great, we'll hear it some other day."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 11/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মাতঙ্গিনী অধীর হইয়া পড়িল, কহিল, “তবে আমি যাই ভাই। দেরি করিলাম বলিয়া আবার কত বকনি খাইতে হইবে। দেখ ভাই, সে দিন আমাদের ওখানে, রাজার জামাই আসিয়াছিলেন, তা’ তিনি যে দিন আসিয়াছিলেন সেই রাত্রেই কাহাকে না বলিয়া চলিয়া গিয়াছেন।”
</prompt>
<result>
Matangini became impatient and said, "Then I'll go, brother. If I delay any further, I'll get another scolding. Listen, brother, that day, the king's son-in-law came to our place, and the very night he arrived, he left without telling anyone."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 12/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলা কহিল, “সত্য নাকি? বটে; কেন বল দেখি; তাই বলি মাতঙ্গ না হইলে আমাকে ভিতরকার খবর কেহ দিতে পারে না।”
</prompt>
<result>
Mangala said, "Really? Of course; tell me why; that's why I say that no one can give me inside news except Matanga."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 13/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মাতঙ্গ প্রফুল্ল হইয়া কহিল, “আসল কথা কি জান? আমাদের যে বৌঠাকরুণটি আছেন, তিনি দুটি চক্ষে কাহারো ভাল দেখিতে পারেন না। তিনি কি মন্তর জানেন, স্বোয়ামীকে একেবারে ভেড়ার মতন করিয়া রাখিয়াছেন, তিনি—না ভাই; কাজ নাই, কে কোথা দিয়া শুনিবে আর বলিবে মাতঙ্গ রাজবাড়ির কথা বাহিরে বলিয়া বেড়ায়।”
</prompt>
<result>
Matanga said cheerfully, "Do you know what the real thing is? Our Bou-Thakurani, she can't see anyone with her two eyes. Does she know some magic, she has kept her husband like a sheep, he—no brother; it's useless, who will listen to you and who will say that Matanga goes around telling the stories of the royal palace outside."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 14/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলা আর কৌতূহল সামলাইতে পারিল না; যদিও সে জানিত, আর খানিকক্ষণ চুপ করিয়া থাকিলে মাতঙ্গ আপনি সমস্ত বলিবে, তবু তাহার বিলম্ব সহিল না, কহিল, “এখানে কোন লোক নাই নাতনী। আর আপনা-আপনির মধ্যে কথা, ইহাতে আর দোষ কি? তা’ তোমাদের বৌঠাকরুণ কি করিলেন?”
</prompt>
<result>
Mangala could not control her curiosity any longer; although she knew that if she remained silent for a while longer, Matanga would tell her everything himself, she could not bear the delay and said, "There is no one here, granddaughter. And what is the harm in talking between ourselves? So what did your Bou-Thakurani do?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 15/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

“তিনি আমাদের দিদিঠাকরুণের নামে জামাইয়ের কাছে কি সব লাগাইয়াছিলেন, তাই জামাই রাতারাতিই দিদিঠাকরুণকে ফেলিয়া চলিয়া গেছেন। দিদিঠাকরুণ ত কাঁদিয়া কাটিয়া অনাত্ত করিতেছেন। মহারাজা খাপা হইয়া উঠিয়াছেন, তিনি বৌঠাকরুণকে শ্রীপুরে বাপের বাড়ি পাঠাইতে চান। ঐ দেখ ভাই, তোমার সকল কথাতেই হাসি! ইহাতে হাসিবার কি পাইলে? তোমার যে আর হাসি ধরে না।”
</prompt>
<result>
"She had put in a good word for her sister-in-law with her son-in-law, and so he left her sister-in-law overnight. Now, the sister-in-law is crying and lamenting. The Maharaja is furious and wants to send Bou-Thakurani back to her father's house in Shreepur. Look brother, you laugh at everything! What's so funny about this? You can't even control your laughter."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 16/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামচন্দ্র রায়ের পলায়ন বার্ত্তার যথার্থ কারণ, রাজবাটির প্রত্যেক দাস দাসী সঠিক অবগত ছিল, কিন্তু কাহারো সহিত কাহারো কথার ঐক্য ছিল না।
</prompt>
<result>
Every servant of the palace knew the real reason behind Ramchandra Roy's escape, but no one discussed it with anyone else.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 17/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলা কহিল, “তোমাদের মাঠাকরুণকে বলিও যে, বৌঠাকরুণকে শীঘ্র বাপের বাড়ি পাঠাইয়া কাজ নাই। মঙ্গলা এমন ওষুধ দিতে পারে যাহাতে যুবরাজের মন তাঁহার উপর হইতে একেবারে চলিয়া যায়।” বলিয়া সে খল্ খল্ করিয়া হাসিতে লাগিল। মাতঙ্গ কহিল, “তা বেশ কথা!”
</prompt>
<result>
Mangala said, "Tell your mother-in-law that there is no need to send Bou-Thakurani back to her father's house so soon. Mangala can give her such a medicine that the prince's mind will completely turn away from her." Saying this, she started laughing loudly. Matanga said, "That's a good idea!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 18/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলা জিজ্ঞাসা করিল, “তোমাদের বৌঠাকরুণকে কি যুবরাজ বড় ভালবাসেন?”
</prompt>
<result>
Mangala asked, "Does the Crown Prince love your Bou-Thakurani very much?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 19/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

“সে কথায় কাজ কি! এক দণ্ড না দেখিলে থাকিতে পারেন না! যুবরাজকে “তু” বলিয়া ডাকিলেই আসেন।”
</prompt>
<result>
"What's the use of talking about it! Can't stay even for a moment without seeing him! Just call the prince 'you' and he'll come."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 20/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

“আচ্ছা, আমি ওষুধ দিব। দিনের বেলাও কি যুবরাজ তাহার কাছেই থাকেন?”
</prompt>
<result>
"Alright, I will give medicine. Does the prince stay with her during the day as well?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 21/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

“হাঁ।”
</prompt>
<result>
"Yes."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 22/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলা কহিল “ওমা কি হইবে! তা’, সে যুবরাজকে কি বলে, কি করে, দেখিয়াছিস?”
</prompt>
<result>
Mangala said, "Oh, what will happen! So, what did you see the prince say and do?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 23/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

“না ভাই, তাহা দেখি নাই।”
</prompt>
<result>
"No brother, I haven't seen that."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 24/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

“আমাকে একবার রাজবাটীতে লইয়া যাইতে পারিস্, আমি তাহা হইলে একবার দেখিয়া আসি!”
</prompt>
<result>
"Can you take me to the palace once, so that I can see it once!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 25/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মাতঙ্গ কহিল “কেন ভাই, তােমার এত মাথাব্যথা কেন?”
</prompt>
<result>
Matanga said, "Why brother, why do you have such a headache?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 26/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলা কহিল, “বলি তা’ নয়। একবার দেখিলেই বুঝিতে পারিব, কি মন্ত্রে সে বশ করিয়াছে, আমার মন্ত্র খাটিবে কি না!”
</prompt>
<result>
Mangala said, "Oh no! I'll understand what spell she has cast on him once I see him. Let's see if my spell works!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 27/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মাতঙ্গ কহিল, “তা’ বেশ, আজ তবে আসি!” বলিয়া চুবড়ি লইয়া চলিয়া গেল।
</prompt>
<result>
Matanga said, "That's great, I'll come today then!" Saying this, he picked up his fishing rod and left.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 14] 28/28</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মাতঙ্গ চলিয়া গেলে মঙ্গলা যেন ফুলিতে লাগিল, দাঁতে দাঁত লাগাইয়া চক্ষু-তারকা প্রসারিত করিয়া বিড়্ বিড়্ করিয়া বকিতে লাগিল।
</prompt>
<result>
When Matanga left, Mangala started to cry, gritting her teeth, widening her eyes, and muttering.
</result>
</query>
</queries>
