<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<queries count="9">
<query>
<info>[Chapter 20] 1/9</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

## বিংশ পরিচ্ছেদ।
</prompt>
<result>
## Chapter 20
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 20] 2/9</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য কিসে সুখে থাকেন, দিনরাত বিভার সেই একমাত্র চেষ্টা। নিজের হাতে সে তাঁহার সমস্ত কাজ করে। সে নিজে তাঁহার খাবার আনিয়া দেয়, আহারের সময় সম্মুখে বসিয়া থাকে, সামান্য বিষয়েও ত্রুটি হইতে দেয় না। যখন সন্ধ্যার সময় উদয়াদিত্য তাঁহার ঘরে আসিয়া বসেন, দুই হাতে চক্ষু আচ্ছাদন করিয়া বসিয়া থাকেন—বুঝি চোখ দিয়া জল পড়িতে থাকে, তখন বিভা আস্তে আস্তে তাঁহার পায়ের কাছে আসিয়া বসে—কথা উত্থাপন করিতে চেষ্টা করে, কিছুই কথা যােগায় না। দুই জনে স্তব্ধ, কাহারও মুখে কথা নাই। মলিন দীপের আলাে মাঝে মাঝে কাঁপিয়া কাঁপিয়া উঠিতেছে, সেই সঙ্গে সঙ্গে দেওয়ালের উপরে একটা আঁধারের ছায়া কাঁপিতেছে, বিভা অনেকক্ষণ ধরিয়া চুপ করিয়া সেই ছায়ার দিকে চাহিয়া চাহিয়া বুক ফাটিয়া নিশ্বাস ফেলিয়া কাঁদিয়া উঠে, “দাদা সে কোথায় গেল?” উদয়াদিত্য চমকিয়া উঠেন, চক্ষুর আচ্ছাদন অপসারণ করিয়া বিভার মুখের দিকে চাহিয়া থাকেন, যেন বিভা কি বলিল ভাল বুঝিতে পারেন নাই, যেন তাহাই বুঝিতে চেষ্টা করিতেছেন, সহসা চৈতন্য হয়, তাড়াতাড়ি চোখের জল মুছিয়া বিভার কাছে আসিয়া বলেন, “আয় বিভা একটা গল্প বলি শোন্!”
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya's only effort day and night is to keep Bibha happy. He does all her work with his own hands. He himself brings her food, sits in front of her during meals, and does not let her suffer even the slightest inconvenience. When Udayaditya comes to his room in the evening and sits down, covering his eyes with both hands and sitting still—perhaps tears start to fall from his eyes—then Bibha slowly comes and sits at his feet—tries to start a conversation, but cannot utter a word. Both of them are silent, neither of them speaks. The light of the dim lamp flickers from time to time, and with it a dark shadow trembles on the wall. Bibha remains silent for a long time, looking at the shadow, her chest heaving with sighs, and she bursts into tears, "Where did he go, Dada?" Udayaditya is startled, removes the covering from his eyes and looks at Bibha's face, as if he did not understand what Bibha said, as if he is trying to understand it, suddenly he regains consciousness, quickly wipes away his tears and comes to Bibha and says, "Come Bibha, let me tell you a story!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 20] 3/9</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বর্ষার দিন—খুব মেঘ করিয়াছে; সমস্ত দিন ঝুপ্ ঝুপ্ করিয়া বৃষ্টি হইতেছে। দিনটা আঁধার করিয়া রহিয়াছে, বাগানের গাছপালাগুলা স্থির ভাবে দাঁড়াইয়া ভিজিতেছে। এক একবার বাতাস দিতেছে ও ঘরের মধ্যে বৃষ্টির ছাঁট আসিতেছে। উদয়াদিত্য চুপ করিয়া বসিয়া আছেন; আকাশে মেঘ ডাকিতেছে, দিগন্তে বিদ্যুত হানিতেছে। বৃষ্টির অবিশ্রাম শব্দ কেবল যেন বলিতেছে, “সুরমা নাই—সে নাই।” মাঝে মাঝে আর্দ্রবাতাস হুহু করিয়া আসিয়া যেন বলিয়া যায়, “সুরমা কোথায়!” বিভা ধীরে ধীরে উদয়াদিত্যের কাছে আসিয়া কহে—“দাদা!” দাদা আর উত্তর দিতে পারেন না, বিভাকে দেখিয়াই তিনি মুখ ঢাকিয়া বাতায়নের উপরে মাথা রাখিয়া পড়েন, মাথার উপরে বৃষ্টি পড়িতে থাকে। এমনি করিয়া দিন চলিয়া যায়, সন্ধ্যা হইয়া আসে, রাত্রি হইতে থাকে। বিভা উদয়াদিত্যের আহারের আয়োজন করিয়া আবার আসিয়া বলে, “দাদা, খাবার আসিয়াছে, খাও’সে!” উদয়াদিত্য কোন উত্তর করেন না। রাত্রি অধিক হইতে লাগিল। বিভা কাঁদিয়া কহে, “দাদা, উঠ, রাত হইল।” উদয়াদিত্য মুখ তুলিয়া দেখেন, বিভা কাঁদিতেছে; তাড়াতাড়ি উঠিয়া বিভার চোখ মুছাইয়া খাইতে যান। ভাল করিয়া খান না। বিভা তাই দেখিয়া নিশ্বাস ফেলিয়া শুইতে যায়, সে আর আহার স্পর্শ করে না।
</prompt>
<result>
It is a rainy day—very cloudy; it has been raining heavily all day long. The day has turned dark, the trees and plants in the garden are standing still and getting drenched. Every now and then the wind blows and raindrops splash inside the house. Udayaditya sits silently; clouds rumble in the sky, lightning strikes in the horizon. The incessant sound of the rain seems to be saying, "Surma is gone—she is no more." Occasionally, the humid wind blows in gusts as if asking, "Where is Surma!" Bibha slowly approaches Udayaditya and says, "Brother!" He cannot respond, upon seeing Bibha, he covers his face, rests his head on the balcony railing, and lets the rain pour on his head. The day passes by like this, evening approaches, and night begins to fall. Bibha arranges Udayaditya's meal and comes back to say, "Brother, food is here, please eat!" Udayaditya does not respond. The night deepens. Bibha cries and says, "Brother, get up, it's night." Udayaditya looks up and sees Bibha crying; he quickly gets up, wipes Bibha's tears, and goes to eat. He does not eat properly. Bibha sighs upon seeing this and goes to bed, she does not eat anything either.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 20] 4/9</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা কথা কহিতে, গল্প করিতে চেষ্টা করে, কিন্তু বিভা অধিক কথা কহিতে পারে না; উদয়াদিত্যকে কি করিয়া যে সুখে রাখিবে ভাবিয়া পায় না। সে কেবল ভাবে, আহা যদি দাদামহাশয় থাকিতেন!
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha tries to talk, to tell stories, but Bibha cannot talk much; she cannot think of how to keep Udayaditya happy. She only thinks, Oh, if only granduncle was here!
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 20] 5/9</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

আজ কাল উদয়াদিত্যের মনে কেমন একটা ভয় উপস্থিত হইয়াছে। তিনি প্রতাপাদিত্যকে অত্যন্ত ভয় করেন। আর সে পূর্ব্বেকার সাহস নাই। বিপদকে তৃণজ্ঞান করিয়া অত্যাচারের বিরুদ্ধে প্রাণপণ করিতে এখন আর পারেন না। সকল কাজেই ইতস্তত করেন, সকল বিষয়েই সংশয় উপস্থিত হয়।
</prompt>
<result>
Nowadays, a kind of fear has arisen in Udayaditya's mind. He is very afraid of Pratapaditya. And he doesn't have the courage he used to have before. He can no longer risk his life against tyranny, considering danger as insignificant. He hesitates in all his actions, and doubts arise in all matters.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 20] 6/9</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

একদিন উদয়াদিত্য শুনিলেন, ছাপরার জমিদারের কাছারীতে রাত্রিযােগে লাঠিয়াল পাঠাইয়া কাছারী লুট করিবার ও কাছারী বাটিতে আগুন লাগাইয়া দিবার আদেশ হইয়াছে। উদয়াদিত্য তৎক্ষণাৎ তাঁহার অশ্ব প্রস্তুত করিতে কহিয়া অন্তঃপুরে গেলেন। শয়নগৃহে প্রবেশ করিয়া একবার চারিদিক দেখিলেন। কি ভাবিতে লাগিলেন। ভাবিতে ভাবিতে অন্যমনস্ক হইয়া বেশ পরিবর্ত্তন করিতে লাগিলেন। বাহিরে আসিলেন। ভৃত্য আসিয়া কহিল, “যুবরাজ অশ্ব প্রস্তুত হইয়াছে। কোথায় যাইতে হইবে?” যুবরাজ কিছুক্ষণ অন্যমনস্ক হইয়া ভৃত্যের মুখের দিকে চাহিয়া রহিলেন ও অবশেষে কহিলেন, “কোথাও না। তুমি অশ্ব লইয়া যাও।”
</prompt>
<result>
One day Udayaditya heard that an order had been given to send lathials to the zamindar's office at Chapara at night to loot the office and set fire to the office building. Udayaditya immediately asked for his horse to be readied and went to the women's quarters. He entered the bedroom and looked around. He started thinking about something. While thinking, he absent-mindedly started changing his clothes. He came out. A servant came and said, "Your Highness, the horse is ready. Where do I take you?" The prince looked at the servant's face absent-mindedly for a while and finally said, "Nowhere. You take the horse away."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 20] 7/9</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

এক দিন এক ক্রন্দনের শব্দ শুনিতে পাইয়া উদয়াদিত্য বাহির হইয়া আসিলেন, দেখিলেন রাজকর্ম্মচারী এক প্রজাকে গাছে বাঁধিয়া মারিতেছে। প্রজা কাঁদিয়া যুবরাজের মুখের দিকে চাহিয়া কহিল, “দোহাই যুবরাজ!” যুবরাজ তাহার যন্ত্রণা দেখিতে পারিলেন না, তাড়াতাড়ি ছুটিয়া গৃহের মধ্যে প্রবেশ করিলেন। আগে হইলে ফলাফল বিচার না করিয়া কর্ম্মচারীকে বাধা দিতেন, প্রজাকে রক্ষা করিতে চেষ্টা করিতেন।
</prompt>
<result>
One day, upon hearing the sound of someone crying, Udayaditya came out and saw a royal official tying a subject to a tree and beating him. The subject cried and looked at the crown prince's face and said, "Oh, Your Highness!" The crown prince could not bear to see his suffering, so he quickly ran and entered the house. In the past, he would have stopped the official without considering the consequences and tried to save the subject.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 20] 8/9</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভাগবত ও সীতারামের বৃত্তি বন্ধ হইয়া গেছে। তাহাদিগকে প্রকাশ্যে অথবা গােপনে অর্থ সাহায্য করিতে যুবরাজের আর সাহস হয় না। যখনি তাহাদের কষ্টের কথা শুনেন, তথনি মনে করেন “আজই আমি টাকা পাঠাইয়া দেব।” তাহার পরেই ইতস্তত করিতে থাকেন, পাঠানো আর হয় না।
</prompt>
<result>
Bhagabat and Sitaram's stipends have been stopped. The crown prince no longer has the courage to help them financially, either openly or secretly. Whenever he hears about their suffering, he thinks to himself, "I will send them money today." But then he starts hesitating and ends up not sending it.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 20] 9/9</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

কেহ যেন না মনে করেন, উদয়াদিত্য প্রাণের ভয়ে এরূপ করিতেছেন। সম্প্রতি জীবনের প্রতি তাঁহার যে পূর্ব্বাপেক্ষা বিশেষ আসক্তি জন্মিয়াছে, তাহা নহে। তাঁহার মনে একটা অন্ধ ভয় উপস্থিত হইয়াছে। প্রতাপাদিত্যকে তিনি যেন রহস্যময় কি একটা মনে করেন! যেন উদয়াদিত্যের অদৃষ্ট, উদয়াদিত্যের ভবিষ্যৎ-জীবনের প্রতিদিন প্রতি মুহূর্ত্ত প্রতাপাদিত্যের মুষ্টির মধ্যে রহিয়াছে। উদয়াদিত্য যখন মৃত্যুকে আলিঙ্গন করিতে যাইতেছেন, জীবনের শেষ মুহূর্ত্তে অবস্থান করিতেছেন, তখনও যদি প্রতাপাদিত্য ভ্রূকুঞ্চিত করিয়া বাঁচিতে আদেশ করেন, তাহা হইলে যেন তখনাে তাঁহাকে মৃত্যুর মুখ হইতে ফিরিয়া আসিতে হইবে।
</prompt>
<result>
Let no one think that Udayaditya is doing this out of fear for his life. It is not that he has recently developed a greater attachment to life than before. A blind fear has arisen in his mind. He thinks of Pratapaditya as some kind of mysterious being! As if Udayaditya's fate, Udayaditya's future life, is in Pratapaditya's fist every day, every moment. Even when Udayaditya is about to embrace death, is in the last moments of his life, if Pratapaditya frowns and orders him to live, then he will have to come back from the jaws of death.
</result>
</query>
</queries>
