<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<queries count="44">
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 1/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

## একবিংশ পরিচ্ছেদ।
</prompt>
<result>
## Chapter Twenty-One.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 2/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিধবা রুক্মিণীর (মঙ্গলার) কিঞ্চিৎ নগদ টাকা আছে। সেই টাকা খাটাইয়া সুদ লইয়া সে জীবিকা নির্ব্বাহ করে। রূপ এবং রূপা এই দুয়ের জোরে সে অনেককে বশে রাখিয়াছে। সীতারাম সৌখীন লােক, অথচ ঘরে এক পয়সার সংস্থান নাই, এইজন্য রুক্মিণীর রূপ ও রূপা উভয়ের প্রতিই তাহার আন্তরিক টান আছে। যে দিন ঘরে হাঁড়ি কাঁদিতেছে, সে দিন সীতারামকে দেখ, দিব্য নিশ্চিন্ত মুখে হাতে লাঠি লইয়া পাতলা চাদর উড়াইয়া বুক ফুলাইয়া রাস্তা দিয়া চলিতেছে, মঙ্গলার বাড়ি যাইবে। পথে যদি কেহ জিজ্ঞাসা করে, “কেমন হে সীতারাম, সংসার কেমন চলিতেছে?” সীতারাম তৎক্ষণাৎ অম্লানবদনে বলে, “বেশ চলিতেছে! কাল আমাদের ওখানে নিমন্ত্রণ রহিল!” সীতারামের বড় বড় কথাগুলা কিছুমাত্র কমে নাই, বরঞ্চ অবস্থা যতই মন্দ হইতেছে কথার পরিমাণ লম্বা ও চওড়ার দিকে ততই বাড়িতেছে। সীতারামের অবস্থাও বড় মন্দ হইতে চলিল। সম্প্রতি এমন হইয়া দাঁড়াইয়াছে যে, পিসা তাঁহার অনারারি পিসা-বৃত্তি পরিত্যাগ করিয়া স্বদেশে ফিরিয়া যাইতে মানস করিতেছেন।
</prompt>
<result>
Widow Rukmini (Mangala) has some cash money. She earns her living by investing that money and taking interest. With the power of her beauty and money, she has kept many people under her control. Sitaram is a carefree person, but he does not have a single penny at home. Therefore, he is sincerely attracted to both Rukmini's beauty and money. On the day when there is no food in the house, you can see Sitaram walking on the street with a stick in his hand, his thin sheet flying, his chest puffed out, and a completely carefree face. He is going to Mangala's house. If someone asks him on the way, "How are you, Sitaram? How is your family doing?" Sitaram immediately says with a smiling face, "It's going great! We have been invited to a feast tomorrow!" Sitaram's big talks have not diminished in the least. Rather, as the situation worsens, the length and breadth of his speech increases. Sitaram's condition is also getting worse. Recently, it has become such that Pisha is thinking of giving up his honorary Pisha scholarship and returning to his homeland.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 3/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

আজ টাকার বিশেষ আবশ্যক হইয়াছে, সীতারাম রুক্মিণীর বাড়িতে আসিয়াছে। হাসিয়া, কাছে ঘেঁসিয়া কহিল—
</prompt>
<result>
Today, there is a special need for money, so Sitaram has come to Rukmini's house. Smiling, he came closer and said—
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 4/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

“ভিক্ষা যদি দেবে রাই,
</prompt>
<result>
"If you give alms, Rai,
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 5/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

(আমার) সােনা রূপায় কাজ নাই,
</prompt>
<result>
(My) gold and silver are of no use,
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 6/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

(আমি) প্রাণের দায়ে এসেছি হে,
</prompt>
<result>
(I) have come at the cost of my life, O
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 7/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মান রতন ভিক্ষা চাই।”
</prompt>
<result>
I beg for the jewel of honor.”
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 8/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

না ভাই, ছড়াটা ঠিক খাটিল না। মান রতনে আমার আপাতত তেমন আবশ্যক নাই, যদি আবশ্যক হয় পরে দেখা যাইবে; আপাতত কিঞ্চিৎ সােনা রূপা পাইলে কাজে লাগে!”
</prompt>
<result>
No brother, the trick didn't quite work. I don't have any immediate need for precious gems, if I do need them I'll see you later; for now, if I get some gold and silver, it will be useful!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 9/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রুক্মিণী সহসা বিশেষ অনুরাগ প্রকাশ করিয়া কহিল, “তা’ তােমার যদি আবশ্যক হইয়া থাকে ত তোমাকে দিব না ত কাহাকে দিব?”
</prompt>
<result>
Rukmini suddenly expressed special affection and said, "If you need it, I won't give it to you, then who will I give it to?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 10/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম তাড়াতাড়ি কহিল, “নাঃ—আবশ্যক এমনিই কি! তবে কি জান ভাই, আমার মার কাছে টাকা থাকে, আমি নিজের হাতে টাকা রাখি না। আজ সকালে মা যােড়াঘাটায় তাঁর জামাইয়ের বাড়ি গিয়াছেন। টাকা বাহির করিয়া দিতে ভুলিয়া গেছেন। তা আমি কালই শােধ করিয়া দিব!”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram hurriedly said, "No—is it really that urgent! But you know brother, my mother keeps the money, I don't keep money in my own hands. Today in the morning, mother went to her son-in-law's house in JoraGhat. She forgot to take out the money. But I will pay you back tomorrow!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 11/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলা মনে মনে হাসিয়া কহিল, “তােমার অত তাড়াতাড়ি করিবার আবশ্যক কি? যখন সুবিধা হয় শােধ দিলেই হইবে। তােমার হাতে দিতেছি, এ ত আর জলে ফেলিয়া দিতেছি না?” জলে ফেলিয়া দিলেও বরঞ্চ পাইবার সম্ভাবনা আছে, সীতারামের হাতে দিলে সে সম্ভাবনা টুকুও নাই, এই প্রভেদ।
</prompt>
<result>
Mangala said with a smile to herself, "Why are you in such a hurry? You can pay whenever it's convenient. I'm giving it to you, I'm not throwing it in the water, am I?" Even if you throw it in the water, there's still a chance of getting it back, but if you give it to Sitaram, there's no chance at all. That's the difference.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 12/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মঙ্গলার এইরূপ অনুরাগের লক্ষণ দেখিয়া সীতারামের ভালবাসা একেবারে উথলিয়া উঠিল। সীতারাম রসিকতা করিবার উদ্যোগ করিল। বিনা টাকায় নবাবী করা ও বিনা হাস্যরসে রসিকতা করা সীতারামের স্বভাবসিদ্ধ। সে যাহা মুখে আসে তাহাই বলে, ও আর কাহারাে অপেক্ষা না করিয়া নিজেই হাসিতে থাকে। তাহার হাসি দেখিয়া হাসি পায়! সে যখন রাজবাড়ির প্রহরী ছিল, তখন আন্যান্য প্রহরীদের সহিত সীতারামের প্রায় মাঝে মঝে দাঙ্গাহাঙ্গামা বাধিবার উদ্যোগ হইত, তাহার প্রধান কারণ, সীতারাম যাহাকে মজা মনে করিত, আর সকলে তাহাকে মজা মনে করিত না। হনুমানপ্রসাদ তেওয়ারি পাহারা দিতে দিতে ঢুলিতে ছিল, সীতারাম আস্তে আস্তে তাহার পশ্চাতে গিয়া হঠাৎ পিঠে এমন এক কিল মারিল যে, সেই হাড়ভাঙ্গা রসিকতার জ্বালায় তাহার পিঠ ও পিত্ত এক সঙ্গে জ্বলিয়া উঠিল। সীতারাম উচ্চৈঃস্বরে হাসিতে লাগিল, কিন্তু হনুমানপ্রসাদ সে হাসিতে যােগ না দিয়া, কিলের সহিত হাস্যরসের প্রভেদ ও করুণ রসের সম্বন্ধ উদাহরণ দ্বারা সীতারামকে অতিশয় স্পষ্ট করিয়া বুঝাইয়া দিয়াছিল। সীতারামের রসিকতার এমন আরো শত শত গল্প এইখানে উদ্ধৃত করা যাইতে পারে।
</prompt>
<result>
Seeing such signs of affection from Mangala, Sitaram's love surged up. Sitaram tried to make jokes. It was Sitaram's nature to act like a nawab without money and to crack jokes without humor. He said whatever came to his mind and laughed without waiting for anyone else. Seeing his laughter made one laugh! When he was a guard at the royal palace, Sitaram and the other guards often got into trouble because Sitaram found things funny that others didn't. Hanumanprasad Tewari was dozing off while on guard duty, and Sitaram slowly went behind him and suddenly kicked him in the back so hard that the pain from that bone-jarring joke made his back and his gall bladder burn at the same time. Sitaram started laughing loudly, but Hanumanprasad didn't join in the laughter. Instead, he used an example to very clearly explain to Sitaram the difference between a kick and a joke and the relationship between humor and pathos. Hundreds of other stories about Sitaram's jokes could be told here.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 13/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

পূর্ব্বেই বলা হইয়াছে সীতারামের অনুরাগ সহসা উথলিত হইয়া উঠিল, সে রুক্মিণীর কাছে ঘেঁসিয়া প্রীতিভরে কহিল, ‘“তুমি আমার সুভদ্রা, আমি তােমার জগন্নাথ।”
</prompt>
<result>
As said before, Sitaram's affection suddenly surged, he moved closer to Rukmini and lovingly said, ""You are my Subhadra, I am your Jagannath.""
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 14/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রুক্মিণী কহিল, “মর্ মিন্সে। সুভদ্রা যে জগন্নাথের বােন!”
</prompt>
<result>
Rukmini said, "Mor Minse. Subhadra is Jagannath's sister!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 15/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম কহিল, “তাহা কেমন করিয়া হইবে? তাহা হইলে সুভদ্রাহরণ হইল কি করিয়া!”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram said, "How can that be? Then how did the abduction of Subhadra happen!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 16/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রুক্মিণী হাসিতে লাগিল, সীতারাম বুক ফুলাইয়া কহিল, “না, তা হইবে না, হাসিলে হইবে না, জবাব দাও! সুভদ্রা যদি বােনই হইল তবে সুভদ্রা হরণ হইল কি করিয়া।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rukmini started laughing, SeetaRam puffed out his chest and said, "No, that won't do, it won't do to laugh, answer me! If Subhadra was your sister, then how did the abduction of Subhadra happen?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 17/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারামের বিশ্বাস যে, সে এমন প্রবল যুক্তি প্রয়ােগ করিয়াছে যে, ইহার উপরে আর কথা কহিবার যাে নাই।
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram believes that he has presented such strong arguments that there is nothing more to be said on the matter.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 18/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রুক্মিণী অতি মিষ্টস্বরে কহিল, “দূর মূর্খ।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rukmini said in a very sweet voice, "Away, fool."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 19/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম গলিয়া গিয়া কহিল, “মূর্খই ত বটে তােমার কাছে আমি ত ভাই হারিয়াই আছি, তােমার কাছে আমি চিরকাল মূর্খ!” সীতারাম মনে মনে ভাবিল, খুব জবাব দিয়াছি, বেশ কথা যােগাইয়াছে।
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram went to the alley and said, "You are such a fool, I have lost my brother to you, I am always a fool to you!" Sitaram thought to himself, I have given a very good answer, I have added good words.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 20/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

আবার কহিল, “আচ্ছা ভাই, কথাটা যদি তােমার পছন্দ না হইল, কি বলিয়া ডাকিলে তুমি খুসী হইবে, আমাকে বল!”
</prompt>
<result>
He said again, "Alright brother, if you don't like the word, what should I call you that would make you happy? Tell me!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 21/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রুক্মিণী হাসিয়া কহিল, “বল প্রাণ।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rukmini said with a smile, "Speak, my dear."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 22/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম কহিল, “প্রাণ!”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram said, "My love!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 23/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রুক্মিণী কহিল, “বল প্রিয়ে।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rukmini said, "Tell me, my love."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 24/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম কহিল, “প্রিয়ে!”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram said, "Darling!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 25/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রুক্মিণী কহিল, “বল প্রিয়তমে!”
</prompt>
<result>
Rukmini said, "Speak, my beloved!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 26/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম কহিল, “প্রিয়তমে!”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram said, "My beloved!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 27/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রুক্মিণী কহিল, “বল প্রাণপ্রিয়ে।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rukmini said, "Speak, my love."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 28/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম কহিল, “প্রাণপ্রিয়ে!”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram said, "My beloved!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 29/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

“আচ্ছা ভাই প্রাণ-প্রিয়ে, তুমি যে টাকাটা দিলে, তাহার সুদ কত লইবে?”
</prompt>
<result>
"Alright brother, my love, how much interest will you charge for the money you gave?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 30/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রুক্মিণী রাগ করিল, মুখ বাঁকাইয়া কহিল, “যাও যাও, এই বুঝি তােমার ভালবাসা! সুদের কথা কোন্ মুখে জিজ্ঞাসা করিলে?”
</prompt>
<result>
Rukmini got angry, turned her face away and said, "Go away, go away, so this is your love! How can you ask me about interest?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 31/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম আনন্দে উচ্ছ্বসিত হইয়া কহিল, “না না, সে কি হয়? আমি কি ভাই সত্য বলিতেছিলাম? আমি যে ঠাট্টা করিতেছিলাম, এইটে আর বুঝিতে পারিলে না? ছি প্রিয়তমে!”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram, elated with joy, exclaimed, "No no, how can that be? Was I speaking the truth, my dear? I was just joking, couldn't you understand that? Fie on you, my beloved!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 32/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারামের মায়ের কি রােগ হইল, জানি না, আজ কাল প্রায় মাঝে মাঝে সে জামাই-বাড়ি যাইতে লাগিল ও টাকা বাহির করিয়া দিবার বিষয়ে তাহার স্মরণশক্তি একেবারে বিলুপ্ত হইয়া গেল! কাজেই সীতারামকে প্রায় মাঝে মাঝে রুক্মিণীর কাছে আসিতে হইত। আজ কাল দেখা যায় সীতারাম ও রুক্মিণীতে মিলিয়া অতি গােপনে কি একটা বিষয় লইয়া পরামর্শ চলিতেছে। অনেকদিন পরামর্শের পর সীতারাম কহিল, “আমার ভাই অত ফন্দি আসে না। এ বিষয়ে ভাগবতের সাহায্য না লইলে চলিবে না।”
</prompt>
<result>
I don't know what illness Sita Ram's mother has, but these days he often visits his in-laws' house and his memory about paying money has completely disappeared! Therefore, Sita Ram had to come to Rukmini's house often. These days it is seen that Sita Ram and Rukmini are secretly discussing something. After a long discussion, Sita Ram said, "My brother is not that clever. We won't be able to do this without Bhagabat's help."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 33/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সেই দিন সন্ধ্যাবেলায় অত্যন্ত ঝড় হইতেছে। রাজবাড়ির ইতস্তত দুম্‌দাম্ করিয়া দরজা পড়িতেছে। বাতাস এমন বেগে বহিতেছে যে, বাগানের বড় বড় গাছের শাখা হেলিয়া ভূমিস্পর্শ করিতেছে। বন্যার মুখে ভগ্ন চূর্ণ গ্রামপল্লীর মত, ঝড়ের মুখে ছিন্নভিন্ন মেঘ ছুটিয়া চলিয়াছে। ঘন ঘন বিদ্যুৎ, ঘন ঘন গর্জ্জন। উদয়াদিত্য চারিদিকের দ্বার রুদ্ধ করিয়া ছােট একটি মেয়েকে কোলে লইয়া বসিয়া আছেন। ঘরের প্রদীপ নিভাইয়া দিয়াছেন। ঘর অন্ধকার। মেয়েটি কোলের উপর ঘুমাইয়া পড়িয়াছে। সুরমা যখন বাঁচিয়াছিল, এই মেয়েটিকে অত্যন্ত ভালবাসিত। সুরমার মৃত্যুর পর ইহার মা ইহাকে আর রাজবাড়িতে পাঠায় নাই। অনেক দিনের পর সে আজ একবার রাজবাড়িতে বেড়াইতে আসিয়াছিল। সহসা উদয়াদিত্যকে দেখিয়া “কাকা” “কাকা” বলিয়া সে তাঁহার কোলের উপরে ঝাঁপাইয়া পড়িয়াছিল। উদয়াদিত্য তাহাকে বুকে চাপিয়া ধরিয়া তাঁহার শয়নগৃহে লইয়া আসিয়াছেন। উদয়াদিত্যের মনের ভাব এই যে, “সুরমা এই মেয়েটিকে যদি একবার দেখিতে আসে! ইহাকে যে সে বড় ভালবাসিত! এত স্নেহের ছিল, সে কি না আসিয়া থাকিতে পারিবে!” মেয়েটি একবার জিজ্ঞাসা করিল, “কাকা, কাকীমা কোথায়?”
</prompt>
<result>
That day in the evening there was a huge storm. The doors of the palace were banging loudly. The wind was blowing so fast that the branches of the big trees in the garden were swaying and touching the ground. Like villages destroyed by floods, the clouds were scattered and running away in the face of the storm. Frequent lightning, frequent thunder. Udayaditya closed all the doors and sat with a little girl in his lap. He had turned off the lamp in the room. The room was dark. The girl fell asleep in his lap. When Surma was alive, she loved this girl very much. After Surma's death, her mother did not send her to the palace anymore. After many days, she came to visit the palace today. Suddenly seeing Udayaditya, she jumped into his lap, calling him "Uncle", "Uncle". Udayaditya hugged her tightly and brought her to his bedroom. Udayaditya thought, "If Surma could see this girl once! How much she loved her! She loved her so much, how could she not come!" The girl asked once, "Uncle, where is Aunty?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 34/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য রুদ্ধকণ্ঠে কহিলেন—“একবার তাঁহাকে ডাক্ না।” মেয়েটি “কাকী মা কাকী মা” করিয়া ডাকিতে লাগিল। উদয়াদিত্যের মনে হইল, ঐ যেন কে সাড়া দিল। দূর হইতে ঐ যেন কে বলিয়া উঠিল, “এই যাই রে!” যেন স্নেহের মেয়েটির করুণ আহ্বান শুনিয়া স্নেহময়ী আর থাকিতে পারিল না, তাহাকে বুকে তুলিয়া লইতে আসিতেছে। বালিকা কোলের উপর ঘুমাইয়া পড়িল। উদয়াদিত্য প্রদীপ নিভাইয়া দিলেন। একটি ঘুমন্ত মেয়েকে কোলে করিয়া অন্ধকার ঘরে একাকী বসিয়া রহিলেন। বাহিরে হুহু করিয়া বাতাস বহিতেছে। ইতস্তত খট্ খট্ করিয়া শব্দ হইতেছে। ঐ না পদশব্দ শুনা গেল? পদশব্দই বটে। বুক এমন দুড়দুড় করিতেছে যে, শব্দ ভাল শুনা যাইতেছে না। দ্বার খুলিয়া গেল, ঘরের মধ্যে দীপালোক প্রবেশ করিল। ইহাও কি কখন সম্ভব! দীপ হস্তে চুপি চুপি ঘরে একটি স্ত্রীলোক প্রবেশ করিল। উদয়াদিত্য চক্ষু মুদ্রিত করিয়া কহিলেন, “সুরমা কি?” পাছে সুরমাকে দেখিলে সুরমা চলিয়া যায়। পাছে সুরমা না হয়।
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya said in a choked voice, "Call her once." The girl started calling, "Aunty, Aunty." Udayaditya felt as if someone responded. From afar, it seemed as if someone said, "I'm coming, my child!" As if the affectionate mother could not resist her affectionate daughter's pitiful call and was coming to take her in her arms. The girl fell asleep in her lap. Udayaditya turned off the lamp. He sat alone in the dark room with a sleeping girl in his arms. The wind was blowing outside. There was a creaking sound here and there. Was that the sound of footsteps? Yes, it was footsteps. His heart was beating so fast that he could not hear the sound properly. The door opened, and light entered the room. Was this even possible? A woman entered the room silently with a lamp in her hand. Udayaditya closed his eyes and said, "Is it Surma?" He was afraid that if he saw Surma, she would go away. He was afraid that it might not be Surma.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 35/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রমণী প্রদীপ রাখিয়া কহিল, “কেন গা, আমাকে কি আর মনে পড়ে না?”
</prompt>
<result>
Ramani kept the lamp and said, "Why, don't you remember me anymore?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 36/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বজ্রধ্বনি শুনিয়া যেন স্বপ্ন ভাঙিল। উদয়াদিত্য চমকিয়া উঠিয়া চক্ষু চাহিলেন। মেয়েটি জাগিয়া উঠিয়া কাকা বলিয়া কাঁদিয়া উঠিল। তাহাকে বিছানার উপরে ফেলিয়া উদয়াদিত্য উঠিয়া দাঁড়াইলেন। কি করিবেন কোথায় যাইবেন যেন ভাবিয়া পাইতেছেন না। রুক্মিণী কাছে আসিয়া মুখ নাড়িয়া কহিল, “বলি, এখন মনে ত পড়িবেই না। তবে এককালে কেন আশা দিয়া আকাশে তুলিয়াছিলে?” উদয়াদিত্য চুপ করিয়া দাঁড়াইয়া রহিলেন, কিছুতেই কথা কহিতে পারিলেন না।
</prompt>
<result>
The sound of thunder broke his dream. Udayaditya woke up with a start and opened his eyes. The girl woke up and started crying, calling him "uncle". Udayaditya got out of bed and stood up, not knowing what to do or where to go. Rukmini came near him and said, "Now you remember me, don't you? Why did you give me hope and then leave me hanging?" Udayaditya stood there silently, unable to say anything.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 37/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

তখন রুক্মিণী তাহার ব্রহ্মাস্ত্র বাহির করিল। কাঁদিয়া কহিল, “আমি তােমার কি দোষ করিয়াছি, যাহাতে তােমার চক্ষুশূল হইলাম। তুমিই ত আমার সর্ব্বনাশ করিয়াছ। যে রমণী যুবরাজকে একদিন দেহ প্রাণ বিকাইয়াছে সে আজ ভিখারিণীর মত পথে পথে বেড়াইতেছে এ পোড়া কপালে বিধাতা কি এই লিখিয়াছিল?”
</prompt>
<result>
Then Rukmini took out her ultimate weapon. She said while crying, "What wrong have I done to you that I have become a thorn in your eyes? You are the one who destroyed me. The woman who sold her body and soul to the crown prince is now wandering on the streets like a beggar. Did the creator write this on my burning forehead?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 38/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

এইবার উদয়াদিত্যের প্রাণে গিয়া আঘাত লাগিল। সহসা তাহার মনে হইল আমিই বুঝি ইহার সর্ব্বনাশ করিয়াছি। অতীতের কথা ভুলিয়া গেলেন। ভুলিয়া গেলেন যৌবনের প্রমত্ত অবস্থায় রুক্মিণী কি করিয়া পদে পদে তাঁহাকে প্রলােভন দেখাইয়াছে, প্রতিদিন তাঁহার পথের সম্মুখে জাল পাতিয়া বসিয়াছিল, আবর্ত্তের মত তাঁহাকে তাহার দুই মােহময় বাহু দিয়া বেষ্টন করিয়া ঘুরাইয়া ঘুরাইয়া মুহূর্ত্তের মধ্যে পাতালের অন্ধকারে নিক্ষেপ করিয়াছিল—সে সমস্তই ভুলিয়া গেলেন। দেখিলেন রুক্মিণীর বসন মলিন, ছিন্ন; রুক্মিণী কঁদিতেছে! করুণহৃদয় উদয়াদিত্য কহিলেন, “তােমার কি চাই?”
</prompt>
<result>
This time Udayaditya's heart was struck with pain. Suddenly he felt that he was the one who had ruined her. He forgot the past. He forgot how Rukmini had tempted him at every step during his wild youth, how she used to lay traps in front of his path every day, how she had surrounded him with her two enchanting arms like a whirlpool and thrown him into the darkness of hell within moments—he forgot all that. He saw that Rukmini's clothes were dirty and torn; Rukmini was crying! The compassionate Udayaditya said, "What do you want?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 39/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রুক্মিণী কহিল, “আমার আর কিছু চাই না, আমার ভালবাসা চাই। আমি ঐ বাতায়নে বসিয়া তােমার বুকে মুখ রাখিয়া তােমার সােহাগ পাইতে চাই। কেন গা, সুরমার চেয়ে কি এ মুখ কালাে? যদি কালােই হইয়া থাকে ত সে তােমার জন্যই পথে পথে ভ্রমণ করিয়া। আগে ত কালো ছিল না।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rukmini said, "I don't want anything else, I want your love. I want to sit in that balcony, rest my head on your chest and receive your affection. Why, is my face darker than Surma's? Even if it is dark, it is because of you, traveling from place to place. It wasn't dark before."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 40/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

এই বলিয়া রুক্মিণী উদয়াদিত্যের শয্যার উপর বসিতে গেল। উদয়াদিত্য আর থাকিতে পারিলেন না। কাতর হইয়া বলিয়া উঠিলেন, “ও বিছানায় বসিও না, বসিও না।”
</prompt>
<result>
Saying this, Rukmini went to sit on Udayaditya's bed. Udayaditya could not bear it any longer. He cried out in anguish, "Oh, don't sit on the bed, don't sit."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 41/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রুক্মিণী আহত ফণিনীর মত মাথা তুলিয়া বলিল, “কেন বসিব না?”
</prompt>
<result>
Rukmini raised her head like a wounded snake and said, "Why shouldn't I sit?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 42/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য তাহার পথ রােধ করিয়া কহিলেন, “না ও বিছানার কাছে তুমি যাইও না! তুমি কি চাও আমি এখনি দিতেছি।”
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya blocked her way and said, "No, don't go near the bed! Whatever you want, I'll give it to you right now."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 43/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রুক্মিণী কহিল, “আচ্ছা তোমার আঙুলের ঐ আংটিটি দাও।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rukmini said, "Alright, give me that ring on your finger."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 21] 44/44</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য তৎক্ষণাৎ তাঁহার হাত হইতে আংটি খুলিয়া ফেলিয়া দিলেন। রুক্মিণী কুড়াইয়া লইয়া বাহির হইয়া গেল। মনে ভাবিল ডাকিনীর মন্ত্রমোহ এখনো দূর হয় নি, আরো কিছুদিন যাক, তাহার পর আমার মন্ত্র খাটিবে। রুক্মিণী চলিয়া গেলে উদয়াদিত্য শয্যার উপরে আসিয়া পড়িলেন। দুই বাহুতে মুখ ঢাকিয়া কাঁদিয়া কহিলেন, “কোথায়, সুরমা কোথায়! আজ আমার এ দগ্ধ বজ্রাহত হৃদয়ে শান্তি দিবে কে?”
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya immediately took the ring off her hand and threw it away. Rukmini picked it up and went outside. She thought to herself, "The spell of the witch is still not broken, let some more days pass, then my spell will work." After Rukmini left, Udayaditya fell on the bed. Covering his face with both hands, he cried and said, "Where, where is Surma! Who will give peace to my burnt and thunderbolt-struck heart today?"
</result>
</query>
</queries>
