<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<queries count="29">
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 1/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

## দ্বাবিংশ পরিচ্ছেদ।
</prompt>
<result>
## Chapter 22
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 2/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভাগবতের অবস্থা বড় ভাল নহে। সে চুপচাপ বসিয়া কয়দিন ধরিয়া অনবরত তামাক ফুঁকিতেছে। ভাগবত যখন মনোযোগের সহিত তামাক ফুঁকিতে থাকে, তখন প্রতিবেশীদের আশঙ্কার কারণ উপস্থিত হয়। কারণ, তাহার মুখ দিয়া কালো কালো ধোঁয়া পাকাইয়া পাকাইয়া উঠিতে থাকে, তাহার মনের মধ্যেও তেমনি একটা কৃষ্ণবর্ণ পাকচক্রের কারখানা চলিতে থাকে। কিন্তু ভাগবত লোকটা বড় ধর্ম্মনিষ্ঠ। সে কাহারো সঙ্গে মেশে না এই যা তাহার দোষ, হরিনামের মালা লইয়া থাকে, অধিক কথা কয় না, পরচর্চ্চায় থাকে না। কিন্তু কেহ যখন ঘোরতর বিপদে পড়ে, তখন ভাগবতের মত পাকা পরামর্শ দিতে আর কেহ পারে না। ভাগবত কখন ইচ্ছা করিয়া পরের অনিষ্ট করে না, কিন্তু আর কেহ যদি তাহার অনিষ্ট করে, তবে ভাগবত ইহজন্মে তাহা কখন ভোলে না, তাহার শোধ তুলিয়া তবে সে হুঁকা নামাইয়া রাখে। এক কথায়—সংসারে যাহাকে ভাল বলে, ভাগবত তাহাই! পাড়ার লোকেরাও তাহাকে মান্য করে, দুরবস্থায় ভাগবত ধার করিয়াছিল, কিন্তু ঘটি বাটি বেচিয়া তাহা শোধ করিয়াছে।
</prompt>
<result>
Bhagabat's condition is not good. He has been sitting silently and smoking tobacco continuously for a few days. When Bhagabat smokes tobacco with concentration, it becomes a cause of concern for the neighbors. Because, black smoke starts coming out of his mouth, and a similar black factory of thoughts starts running in his mind. But Bhagabat is a very religious person. He doesn't socialize with anyone, that's his only fault. He keeps a garland of holy basil beads, doesn't talk much, and doesn't gossip. But when someone falls into serious trouble, no one can give better advice than Bhagabat. Bhagabat never intentionally harms others, but if someone else harms him, Bhagabat never forgets it in this life. He takes revenge and only then puts down his hookah. In a word, Bhagabat is what is called a good person in the world! The people of the neighborhood also respect him. Bhagabat had borrowed money during difficult times, but he has repaid it by selling his utensils.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 3/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

একদিন সকালে সীতারাম আসিয়া ভাগবতকে জিজ্ঞাসা করিল “দাদা কেমন আছ হে?”
</prompt>
<result>
One morning, Sitaram came and asked Bhagavat, "Brother, how are you?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 4/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভাগবত কহিল, “ভাল না।”
</prompt>
<result>
Bhagavat said, "Not good."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 5/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম কহিল, “কেন বল দেখি?”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram said, "Why, tell me?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 6/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভাগবত কিয়ৎক্ষণ তামাক টানিয়া সীতারামের হাতে হুঁকা দিয়া কহিল “বড় টানাটানি পড়িয়াছে।”
</prompt>
<result>
Bhagbhat smoked tobacco for a while and then handed the hookah to Sitaram, saying, "There's a lot of tension."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 7/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম কহিল “বটে? তা কেমন করিয়া হইল?”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram said, "Really? How did that happen?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 8/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভাগবত মনে মনে কিঞ্চিৎ রুষ্ট হইয়া কহিল, “কেমন করিয়া হইল? তােমাকেও তাহা বলিতে হইবে না কি? আমি ত জানিতাম আমারো যে দশা তােমারো সে দশা!”
</prompt>
<result>
Bhagbhat, slightly annoyed in his mind, said, "How did it happen? Do you have to tell me that too? I knew that my condition is the same as yours!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 9/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম কিছু অপ্রস্তুত হইয়া কহিল, “না, হে, আমি সে কথা কহিতেছি না, আমি বলিতেছি তুমি ধার কর না কেন?”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram said with some hesitation, "No, I am not saying that, I am asking why don't you borrow?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 10/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভাগবত কহিল, “ধার করিলে ত শুধিতে হইবে। শুধিব কি দিয়া? বিক্রি করিবার ও বাঁধা দিবার জিনিষ বড় অধিক নাই।”
</prompt>
<result>
Bhagavat said, "If you take a loan, you will have to pay it back. How will you pay it back? You don't have many things to sell or mortgage."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 11/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম সগর্ব্বে কহিল, “তােমার কত টাকা ধার চাই, আমি দিব।”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram said proudly, "How much money do you need to borrow, I will give it to you."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 12/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভাগবত কহিল, “বটে? তা এতই যদি তােমার টাকা হইয়া থাকে যে, এক মুঠা জলে ফেলিয়া দিলেও কিছু না আসে যায়, তা হইলে আমাকে গােটা দশেক দিয়া ফেল। কিন্তু আগে হইতে বলিয়া রাখিতেছি, আমার শুধিবার শক্তি নাই!”
</prompt>
<result>
Bhagavat said, "Really? If you have so much money that throwing a handful into the water doesn't matter, then give me ten coins. But I'm telling you in advance, I don't have the power to purify!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 13/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম কহিল, “সে জন্যে, দাদা, তােমাকে ভাবিতে হইবে না।”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram said, "For that, Dada, you don't have to worry."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 14/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারামের কাছে এইরূপ সাহায্যপ্রাপ্তির আশা পাইয়া ভাগবত বন্ধুতার উচ্ছ্বাসে যে নিতান্ত উচ্ছ্বসিত হইয়া উঠিয়াছিল, তাহা নহে। আর এক ছিলিম তামাক সাজিয়া চুপ করিয়া বসিয়া টানিতে লাগিল।
</prompt>
<result>
Upon receiving such help from Sitaram, Bhagavat did not become overly excited with the enthusiasm of friendship. He prepared another chillum of tobacco, sat down silently, and began to smoke.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 15/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম আস্তে আস্তে কথা পাড়িল—“দাদা, রাজার অন্যায় বিচারে আমাদের ত অন্ন মারা গেল।”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram slowly started a conversation, "Brother, because of the king's unjust judgment, we are starving."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 16/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভাগবত কহিল—“কই, তােমার ভাবে ত তাহা বােধ হইল না!” সীতারামের বদান্যতা ভাগবতের বড় সহ্য হয় নাই, মনে মনে কিছু চটিয়াছিল!
</prompt>
<result>
Bhagabat said - "Well, it didn't seem like that from your expressions!" Bhagabat couldn't tolerate Sitaram's generosity, he was a little annoyed in his mind!
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 17/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম কহিল, “না, ভাই কথার কথা বলিতেছি! আজ না যায় ত দশদিন পরে ত যাইবে।”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram said, "No, brother, I am speaking the truth! If you don't go today, you will have to go after ten days."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 18/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভাগবত কহিল—“তা, রাজা যদি অন্যায় বিচার করেন ত আমরা কি করিতে পারি।”
</prompt>
<result>
Bhagavat said - "Well, if the king delivers an unjust verdict, what can we do?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 19/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম কহিল, “আহা যুবরাজ যখন রাজা হইবে, তখন যশােরে রামরাজত্ব হইবে ততদিন যেন আমরা বাঁচিয়া থাকি।”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram said, "Alas, when the crown prince becomes the king, then Ramrajya will be established in Jashore. May we live to see that day."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 20/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভাগবত চটিয়া গিয়া কহিল, “ওসব কথায় আমাদের কাজ কি ভাই? তুমি বড়মানুষ লােক, তুমি নিজের ঘরে বসিয়া রাজা উজীর মার, সে শােভা পায়—আমি গরীব মানুষ, আমার অতটা ভরসা হয় না!”
</prompt>
<result>
Bhagavat got annoyed and said, "What do we have to do with all this talk, brother? You are a great man, you can sit in your own house and kill the king and the minister, that's fine—I am a poor man, I don't have that much confidence!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 21/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম কহিল, “রাগ কর কেন দাদা? কথাটা মন দিয়া শােনই না কেন?” বলিয়া চুপি চুপি কি বলিতে লাগিল।
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram said, "Why are you angry, brother? Why don't you listen to what I have to say?" Saying this, he started to say something in a hushed tone.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 22/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভাগবত মহাক্রুদ্ধ হইয়া বলিল, “দেখ, সীতারাম আমি তােমাকে স্পষ্ট করিয়া বলিতেছি, আমার কাছে অমন কথা তুমি মুখে উচ্চারণ করিও না।”
</prompt>
<result>
Bhagbhat became furious and said, "Listen, Sitaram, I am telling you clearly, don't you dare utter such words in front of me."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 23/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম সে দিন ত চলিয়া গেল। ভাগবত ভারি মনােযােগ দিয়া সমস্ত দিন কি একটা ভাবিতে লাগিল, তাহার পরদিন সকাল বেলায় সে নিজে সীতারামের কাছে গেল। সীতারামকে কহিল, “কাল যে কথাটা বলিয়াছিলে বড় পাকা কথা বলিয়াছিলে।”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram left that day. Bhagabat spent the whole day thinking about something with great concentration, the next morning he himself went to Sitaram. He said to Sitaram, "The thing you said yesterday was very wise."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 24/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম গর্ব্বিত হইয়া উঠিয়া কহিল, “কেমন দাদা বলি নাই!”
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram proudly said, "Didn't I tell you, brother!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 25/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভাগবত কহিল, “আজ সেই বিষয়ে তােমার সঙ্গে পরামর্শ করিতে আসিয়াছি।”
</prompt>
<result>
Bhagabat said, "I have come to consult you about that matter today."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 26/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সীতারাম আরাে গর্ব্বিত হইয়া উঠিল। কয়দিন ধরিয়া ক্রমিক পরামর্শ চলিতে লাগিল।
</prompt>
<result>
Sitaram became even more proud. For a few days, gradual consultation began to take place.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 27/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

পরামর্শ করিয়া যাহা স্থির হইল, তাহা এই, একটা জাল দরখাস্ত লিখিতে হইবে, যেন যুবরাজ প্রতাপাদিত্যের নামে সম্রাট-বিদ্রোহিতার অভিযােগ করিয়া নিজে রাজ্য পাইবার জন্য দরখাস্ত করিতেছেন। তাহাতে যুবরাজের শীল-মােহর মুদ্রিত থাকিবে। রুক্মিণী যে আংটিটি লইয়া আসিয়াছে, তাহাতে যুবরাজের নাম মুদ্রাঙ্কিত শীল আছে, অতএব কাজ অনেকটা অগ্রসর হইয়া আছে।
</prompt>
<result>
After consultation, it was decided that a forged petition would be written, in which it would be alleged that Crown Prince Pratapaditya was planning to rebel against the emperor in order to seize the kingdom for himself. The petition would bear the Crown Prince's seal. Rukmini had brought a ring that bore the Crown Prince's seal engraved with his name, so the plan was already well underway.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 28/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

পরামর্শমত কাজ হইল। একখানা জাল দরখাস্ত লেখা হইল, তাহাতে যুবরাজের নাম মুদ্রিত রহিল। নির্ব্বোধ সীতারামের উপর নির্ভর করা যায় না, অতএব স্থির হইল, ভাগবত নিজে দরখাস্ত লইয়া দিলীশ্বরের হস্তে সমর্পণ করিবে।
</prompt>
<result>
The work was done as advised. A draft application was written, in which the name of the prince was printed. Ignorant Sitaram cannot be relied upon, therefore it was decided that Bhagabat himself would take the application and hand it over to Dilishwar.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 22] 29/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভাগবত সেই দরখাস্তখানি লইয়া দিল্লীর দিকে না গিয়া প্রতাপ আদিত্যের কাছে গেল। মহারাজকে কহিল, “উদয়াদিত্যের এক ভৃত্য এই দরখাস্তটি লইয়া দিল্লীর দিকে যাইতেছিল, আমি কোন সূত্রে জানিতে পারি। ভৃত্যটা দেশ ছাড়িয়া পলাইয়া গেছে, দরখাস্তটি লইয়া আমি মহারাজার নিকট আসিতেছি।” ভাগবত সীতারামের নাম করে নাই। দরখাস্ত পাঠ করিয়া প্রতাপাদিত্যের কি অবস্থা হইল তাহা আর বলিবার আবশ্যক করে না। ভাগবতের পুনর্ব্বার রাজবাড়িতে চাক্‌রী হইল।
</prompt>
<result>
Bhagabat took the petition and instead of going to Delhi, he went to Pratap Aditya. He told the Maharaja, "One of Udayaditya's servants was taking this petition to Delhi, I somehow found out. The servant has fled the country, I am bringing the petition to the Maharaja." Bhagabat did not mention Sitaram's name. It is needless to say what Pratap Aditya's condition was after reading the petition. Bhagabat got his job back in the palace.
</result>
</query>
</queries>
