<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<queries count="29">
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 1/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

## ত্রয়ােবিংশ পরিচ্ছেদ।
</prompt>
<result>
## Chapter 23
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 2/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভার প্রাণের মধ্যে আঁধার করিয়া আসিয়াছে। ভবিষ্যতে কি যেন একটা মর্ম্মভেদী দুঃখ, একটা মরুময়ী নিরাশা, জীবনের সমস্ত সুখের জলাঞ্জলি, তাহার জন্য অপেক্ষা করিয়া আছে, প্রতি মুহূর্ত্তে তাহার কাছে কাছে সরিয়া আসিতেছে। সেই যে জীবনশূন্যকারী চরাচরগ্রাসী শুষ্ক সীমাহীন ভবিষ্যৎ অদৃষ্টের আশঙ্কা, তাহারি একটা ছায়া আসিয়া যেন বিভার প্রাণের মধ্যে পড়িয়াছে। বিভার মনের ভিতরে কেমন করিতেছে! বিভা বিছানায় একেলা পড়িয়া আছে। এ সময়ে বিভার কাছে কেহ নাই। বিভা নিশ্বাস ফেলিয়া বিভা কাঁদিয়া বিভা আকুল হইয়া কহিল, “আমাকে কি তবে পরিত্যাগ করিলে? আমি তােমার কি অপরাধ করিয়াছি?” কাঁদিয়া কাঁদিয়া কহিতে লাগিল, “আমি কি অপরাধ করিয়াছি?” দুটি হাতে মুখ ঢাকিয়া বালিশ বুকে লইয়া কাঁদিয়া কাঁদিয়া বার বার করিয়া কহিল “আমি কি করিয়াছি?” “একখানি পত্র না, একটি লােকও আসিল না, কাহারো মুখে সংবাদ শুনিতে পাই না। আমি কি করিব? বুক ফাটিয়া ছট্ ফট্ করিয়া সমস্ত দিন ঘরে ঘরে ঘুরিয়া বেড়াইতেছি, কেহ তােমার সংবাদ বলে না, কাহারো মুখে তােমার নাম শুনিতে পাই না! মা গো মা দিন কি করিয়া কাটিবে!” এমন কত দিন গেল। এমন কত মধ্যাহ্নে কত অপরাহ্ণে কত রাত্রে সঙ্গীহীন বিভা রাজবাড়ির শূন্য ঘরে ঘরে একখানি শীর্ণ ছায়ার মত ঘুরিয়া বেড়ায়!
</prompt>
<result>
Darkness has enveloped Bibha's soul. In the future, some heart-wrenching sorrow, a despairing desolation, the renunciation of all the happiness of life, awaits her, approaching her with each passing moment. The fear of that life-draining, all-consuming, dry, boundless, uncertain future has cast a shadow upon Bibha's soul. What is Bibha feeling in her heart? Bibha lies alone on her bed. At this moment, Bibha has no one by her side. Bibha sighed, Bibha cried, Bibha became distraught and said, "Have you abandoned me? What wrong have I done to you?" She continued to cry and say, "What wrong have I done?" Covering her face with both hands, she held the pillow to her chest and cried repeatedly, "What have I done?" "Not a single letter, not a single person has come, I hear no news from anyone's mouth. What am I to do? My heart is breaking, I am pacing restlessly from room to room all day long, no one tells me any news of you, I hear your name from no one's mouth! Mother, oh mother, how will I pass the days!" How many days have passed like this? How many afternoons, how many evenings, how many nights has Bibha, bereft of companionship, wandered like a thin shadow through the empty rooms of the palace!
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 3/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

এমন সময় একদিন প্রাতঃকালে রামমােহন আসিয়া “মা গাে জয় হােক্” বলিয়া প্রণাম করিল, বিভা এমনি চমকিয়া উঠিল, যেন তাহার মাথায় একটা সুখের বজ্র ভাঙিয়া পড়িল। তাহার চোখ দিয়া জল বাহির হইল। সে সচকিত হইয়া কহিল, “মােহন, তুই এলি!”
</prompt>
<result>
One day at such a time, Rammohan came in the morning and said, "Mother, victory to you," and bowed down to her. Bibha was so startled, as if a thunderbolt of happiness had struck her head. Tears came out of her eyes. She became alert and said, "Mohan, you came!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 4/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

“হাঁ মা, দেখিলাম, মা আমাদের ভুলিয়া গেছেন, তাঁহাকে একবার স্মরণ করাইয়া আসি!”
</prompt>
<result>
"Yes mother, I saw that mother has forgotten us, let me go and remind her once!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 5/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা কত কি জিজ্ঞাসা করিবে মনে করিল কিন্তু লজ্জায় পারিল না—বলে বলে করিয়া হইয়া উঠিল না—অথচ শুনিবার জন্য প্রাণটা ব্যাকুল হইয়া রহিল।
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha thought of asking so many things but couldn't due to shyness—couldn't bring herself to ask—yet her heart was eager to hear.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 6/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমােহন বিভার মুখের দিকে চাহিয়া কহিল, “কেন মা, তােমার মুখখানি অমন মলিন কেন? তােমার চোখে কালি পড়িয়াছে। মুখে হাসি নাই। চুল রুক্ষ। এস মা, আমাদের ঘরে এস। এখানে বুঝি তােমাকে যত্ন করিবার কেহ নাই!”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan looked at Bibha's face and said, "Why, mother, why is your face so gloomy? There are dark circles under your eyes. There is no smile on your face. Your hair is rough. Come, mother, come to our house. I guess there is no one here to take care of you!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 7/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা ম্লান হাসি হাসিল; কিছু কহিল না! হাসিতে হাসিতে হাসি আর রহিলনা। দুই চক্ষু দিয়া জল পড়িতে লাগিল—শীর্ণ বিবর্ণ দুটি কপােল প্লাবিত করিয়া জল পড়িতে লাগিল, অশ্রু আর থামে না! বহু। দিন অনাদরের পর একটু আদর পাইলে যে অভিমান উথলিয়া উঠে, বিভা সেই অতি কোমল, মৃদু, অনন্ত প্রীতিপূর্ণ অভিমানে কাঁদিয়া ফেলিল। মনে মনে কহিল, “এত দিন পরে কি আমাকে মনে পড়িল?”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha gave a faint smile; she didn't say anything! Her laughter gradually faded away. Tears started to fall from her eyes—flooding her thin, pale cheeks, the tears wouldn't stop! After so many days of neglect, when she received a little affection, the resentment welled up inside her. Bibha burst into tears with that very tender, gentle, infinitely loving resentment. She thought to herself, "After all this time, he remembered me?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 8/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমােহন অর থাকিতে পারিল না, তাহার চোখে জল আসিল, কহিল—“একি অলক্ষণ! মা-লক্ষ্মী তুমি হাসি মুখে আমাদের ঘরে এস। আজ শুভ দিনে চোখের জল মােছ!”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan couldn't hold himself back, tears welled up in his eyes, he said - "What a bad omen! Goddess Lakshmi, please come to our house with a smiling face. Please wipe away the tears from our eyes on this auspicious day!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 9/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মহিষীর মনে মনে ভয় ছিল, পাছে জামাই তাঁর মেয়েকে গ্রহণ না করে। রামমোহন বিভাকে লইতে আসিয়াছে শুনিয়া তাঁহার অত্যন্ত আনন্দ হইল। তিনি রামমোহনকে ডাকাইয়া জামাই-বাড়ির কুশল জিজ্ঞাসা করিলেন, বিশেষ যত্নে রামমােহনকে আহার করাইলেন, রামমােহনের গল্প শুনিলেন, আনন্দে দিন কাটিল! কাল যাত্রার দিন ভাল; কাল প্রভাতেই বিভাকে পাঠাইবেন স্থির হইল। প্রতাপাদিত্য এ বিষয়ে আর কিছু আপত্তি করিলেন না।
</prompt>
<result>
The queen was afraid in her mind, lest her son-in-law does not accept her daughter. She was very happy to hear that Rammohan has come to take Bibha. She called Rammohan and asked about the well-being of his family, fed Rammohan with special care, listened to Rammohan's stories, and spent the day in joy! Tomorrow is a good day for the journey; she decided to send Bibha tomorrow morning. Pratapaditya did not object to this anymore.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 10/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

যাত্রার যখন সমস্তই স্থির হইয়া গেছে, তখন বিভা একবার উদয়াদিত্যের কাছে গেল! উদয়াদিত্য একাকী বসিয়া কি একটা ভাবিতেছিলেন।
</prompt>
<result>
When everything for the journey was finalized, Bibha went to Udayaditya. Udayaditya was sitting alone, thinking about something.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 11/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভাকে দেখিয়া সহসা ঈষৎ চমকিত হইয়া কহিলেন, “বিভা, তবে তুই চলিলি? তা’ ভালই হইল! তুই সুখে থাকিতে পারিবি। আশীর্ব্বাদ করি—লক্ষ্মীস্বরূপা হইয়া স্বামীর ঘর উজ্জ্বল করিয়া থাক্!”
</prompt>
<result>
Seeing Bibha, he was slightly startled and said, "Bibha, so you are leaving? Well, that's good! You will be happy. I bless you—may you be like Lakshmi and brighten your husband's home!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 12/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা উদয়াদিত্যের পায়ের কাছে পড়িয়া কাঁদিতে লাগিল। উদয়াদিত্যের চোখ দিয়া জল পড়িতে লাগিল;—বিভার মাথায় হাত দিয়া তিনি কহিলেন,—“কেন কাঁদিতেছিস? এখানে তাের কি সুখ ছিল বিভা; চারিদিকে কেবল দুঃখ, কষ্ট, শােক। এ কারাগার হইতে পালাইলি—তুই বাঁচিলি!”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha fell at Udayaditya's feet and started crying. Tears started flowing from Udayaditya's eyes;—placing his hand on Bibha's head he said,—“Why are you crying? What happiness did you have here Bibha; all around there was only sorrow, pain, grief. You escaped from this prison—you are saved!”
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 13/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা যখন উঠিল, তখন উদয়াদিত্য কহিলেন, “যাইতেছিস্? তবে আয়। স্বামীগৃহে গিয়া আমাদের একেবারে যেন ভুলিয়া যাস্‌নে। এক এক বার মনে করিস্‌, মাঝে মাঝে যেন সংবাদ পাই।”
</prompt>
<result>
When Bibha got up, Udayaditya said, "Are you leaving? Then come. I hope you won't forget us completely after going to your husband's house. Remember us sometimes, and send us news from time to time."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 14/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা রামমােহনের কাছে গিয়া কহিল, “এখন আমি যাইতে পারিব না!”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha went to Rammohan and said, "I can't go now!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 15/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমােহন বিস্মিত হইয়া কহিল, “সে কি কথা মা?”
</prompt>
<result>
Ramamohan said in surprise, "What are you saying, mother?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 16/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা কহিল, “না, আমি যাইতে পারিব না। দাদাকে আমি এখন একলা ফেলিয়া যাইতে পারিব না। আমা হইতেই তাঁহার এত কষ্ট এত দুঃখ, আর আমি আজ তাঁহাকে এখানে ফেলিয়া রাখিয়া সুখ ভােগ করিতে যাইব? যত দিন তাঁহার মনে তিলমাত্র কষ্ট থাকিবে, তত দিন আমিও তাঁহার সঙ্গে সঙ্গে থাকিব। এখানে আমার মত তাঁহাকে কে যত্ন করিবে?” বলিয়া বিভা কাঁদিয়া চলিয়া গেল।
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha said, "No, I cannot go. I cannot leave Dada alone now. All this pain and suffering of his is because of me, and today I will leave him here and go to enjoy myself? As long as there is even a tiny bit of pain in his mind, I will stay with him. Who else will take care of him like I do?" Saying this, Bibha cried and left.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 17/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

অন্তঃপুরে একটা গোলযােগ বাধিয়া উঠিল। মহিষী আসিয়া বিভাকে তিরস্কার করিতে লাগিলেন; তাহাকে অনেক ভয় দেখাইলেন, অনেক পরামর্শ দিলেন; বিভা কেবল কহিল—“না মা, আমি পারিব না!”
</prompt>
<result>
A commotion broke out in the women's quarters. The queen came and started rebuking Bibha; she threatened her with dire consequences and gave her a lot of advice; Bibha simply said—"No mother, I can't do it!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 18/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মহিষী রােষে বিরক্তিতে কাঁদিয়া কহিলেন, “এমন মেয়েও ত কোথাও দেখি নাই!” তিনি মহারাজের কাছে গিয়া সমস্ত কহিলেন। মহারাজ প্রশান্ত ভাবে কহিলেন, “তা, বেশ ত, বিভার যদি ইচ্ছা না হয় ত কেন যাইবে?”
</prompt>
<result>
The queen, vexed and annoyed, said tearfully, "I have never seen such a girl anywhere!" She went to the king and told him everything. The king calmly said, "Well then, if Bibha doesn't want to go, why should she?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 19/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মহিষী অবাক্ হইয়া, হাত উল্টাইয়া, হাল ছাড়িয়া দিয়া কহিলেন, —“তােমাদের যাহা ইচ্ছা তাহাই কর, আমি আর কোন কথায় থাকিব না।”
</prompt>
<result>
The queen was astonished, she turned her hand, let go of the plough and said, "Do whatever you want, I will not say anything more."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 20/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

উদয়াদিত্য সমস্ত শুনিয়া বিস্মিত হইলেন। তিনি বিভাকে আসিয়া অনেক করিয়া বুঝাইলেন; বিভা চুপ করিয়া কাঁদিতে লাগিল, ভাল বুঝিল না!
</prompt>
<result>
Udayaditya was astonished after hearing everything. He came to Bibha and tried to make her understand a lot; Bibha started crying silently, she didn't understand properly!
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 21/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

হতাশ্বাস রামমােহন আসিয়া ম্লানমুখে কহিল, “মা, তবে চলিলাম। মহারাজকে গিয়া কি বলিব?”
</prompt>
<result>
Hopeless Rammohan came and said with a gloomy face, "Mother, then I shall leave. What shall I tell the Maharaja?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 22/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা কিছু বলিতে পারিল না, অনেক ক্ষণ নিরুত্তর হইয়া রহিল!
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha couldn't say anything, she remained silent for a long time!
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 23/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমােহন কহিল, “তবে বিদায় হই মা!” বলিয়া প্রণাম করিয়া উঠিয়া গেল। বিভা একেবারে আকুল হইয়া কাঁদিয়া উঠিল, কাতর স্বরে ডাকিল “মােহন!”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan said, "Then goodbye mother!" Saying this, he bowed down and left. Bibha started crying in distress, and called out in a plaintive voice, "Mohan!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 24/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মােহন ফিরিয়া আসিয়া কহিল, “কি মা?”
</prompt>
<result>
Mohan returned and said, "What is it, mother?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 25/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা কহিল, “মহারাজকে বলিও, আমাকে যেন মার্জ্জনা করেন। তিনি স্বয়ং ডাকিতেছেন, তবু আমি যাইতে পারিলাম না, সে কেবল নিতান্তই আমার দুরদৃষ্ট?”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha said, "Tell Maharaj, to please forgive me. Even though he himself is calling me, I couldn't go, is it just my sheer bad luck?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 26/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমােহন শুষ্কভাবে কহিল, “যে আজ্ঞা!”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan said dryly, "As you command!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 27/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমােহন আবার প্রণাম করিয়া বিদায় হইয়া গেল। বিভা দেখিল, রামমােহান বিভার ভাব কিছুই বুঝিতে পারে নাই, তাহার ভারি গােলমাল ঠেকিয়াছে। একে ত বিভার প্রাণ যেখানে যাইতে চায়, বিভা সেখানে যাইতে পারিল না;—তাহার উপর রামমােহন, যাহাকে সে যথার্থ স্নেহ করে, সে আজ রাগ করিয়া চলিয়া গেল। বিভার প্রাণে যাহা হইল তাহা বিভাই জানে!
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan bowed again and took his leave. Bibha noticed that Rammohan couldn't understand her feelings at all, he seemed very confused. On one hand, Bibha couldn't go where her heart desired; on top of that, Rammohan, whom she truly loved, left angrily today. Only Bibha knows what happened to her soul!
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 28/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা রহিল। চোখের জল মুছিয়া প্রাণের মধ্যে পাষাণ-ভার বহিয়া সে তাহার দাদার কাছে পড়িয়া রহিল। ম্লান, শীর্ণ একখানি ছায়ার মত সে নীরবে সমস্ত ঘরের কাজ করে। উদয়াদিত্য স্নেহ করিয়া, আদর করিয়া কোন কথা কহিলে চোখ নীচু করিয়া একটুখানি হাসে। সন্ধ্যাবেলায় উদয়াদিত্যের পায়ের কাছে বসিয়া একটু কথা কহিতে চেষ্টা করে। যখন মহিষী তিরস্কার করিয়া কিছু বলেন, চুপ করিয়া দাঁড়াইয়া শােনে, ও অবশেষে এক খণ্ড মলিন মেঘের মত ভাসিয়া চলিয়া যায়। যখন কেহ বিভার চিবুক ধরিয়া বলে, “বিভা তুই এত রােগা হতেছিস্ কেন?” বিভা কিছু বলে না, কেবল একটু হাসে।
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha remained. Wiping away her tears and carrying the weight of a stone in her heart, she fell at her grandfather's feet. Pale and thin, like a shadow, she silently did all the household chores. When Udayaditya showed her affection and asked her something, she lowered her eyes and smiled a little. In the evening, she tried to talk a little while sitting at Udayaditya's feet. When the queen scolded her and said something, she stood silently and listened, and finally drifted away like a piece of dark cloud. When someone held Bibha's chin and said, "Bibha, why are you getting so thin?" Bibha didn't say anything, she just smiled a little.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 23] 29/29</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

এই সময়ে ভাগবত পূর্ব্বোক্ত জাল দরখাস্তটি লইয়া প্রতাপাদিত্যকে দেখায়, প্রতাপাদিত্য আগুন হইয়া উঠিলেন—পরে অনেক বিবেচনা করিয়া উদয়াদিত্যকে কারারুদ্ধ করিবার আদেশ দিলেন। মন্ত্রী কহিলেন, “মহারাজ, যুবরাজ যে একাজ করিয়াছেন, ইহা কোন মতেই বিশ্বাস হয় না। যে শোনে সেই জিভ কাটিয়া বলে, ওকথা কানে আনিতে নাই। যুবরাজ একাজ করিবেন ইহা বিশ্বাসযােগ্য নহে।” প্রতাপাদিত্য কহিলেন, “আমারাে ত বড় একটা বিশ্বাস হয় না। কিন্তু তাই বলিয়া কারাগারে থাকিতে দোষ কি? সেখানে কোন প্রকার কষ্ট না দিলেই হইল। কেবল গােপনে কিছু না করিতে পারে তাহার জন্য পাহারা নিযুক্ত থাকিবে।”
</prompt>
<result>
At this time, Bhagavat shows Pratapaditya the aforementioned forged petition, Pratapaditya became furious—after much deliberation, he ordered Udayaditya to be imprisoned. The minister said, "Your Majesty, it is impossible to believe that the crown prince has done this. Whoever hears it, their tongue will be cut off for saying it, it is unbearable to hear. It is not believable that the crown prince would do this." Pratapaditya said, "We don't really believe it either. But what harm is there in keeping him in prison? As long as he is not subjected to any hardship there. Only guards will be posted so that he cannot do anything in secret."
</result>
</query>
</queries>
