<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<queries count="31">
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 1/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

## ষট্‌ত্রিংশ পরিচ্ছেদ।
</prompt>
<result>
## Chapter 36
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 2/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

আজ লােজনেরা ভারি ব্যস্ত। চারিদিকে বাজনা বাজিতেছে। গ্রামে যেন একটি উৎসব পড়িয়াছে। একে বিভার প্রাণে অধীর আনন্দ জাগিতেছে, তাহার পরে চারিদিকে বাজনার শব্দ শুনিয়া তাহায় হৃদয় যেন উচ্ছসিত হইয়া উঠিল। পাছে উদয়াদিত্যের কাছে তাহার এই অত্যধিক আনন্দ প্রকাশ হইয়া পড়ে, এই জন্য কত কষ্টে সে হাসি নিবারণ করিয়া রাখিয়াছে! উদয়াদিত্য নদী-তীরে উৎসবের ভাব দেখিয়া কি হইতেছে জানিবার জন্য গ্রামে বেড়াইতে গেলেন।
</prompt>
<result>
Today, the servants are very busy. Music is playing all around. It is as if there is a festival in the village. On the one hand, Bibha's heart is filled with uncontrollable joy, and on the other hand, hearing the sound of music all around, her heart feels like it is overflowing. How hard she tries to suppress her laughter, lest Udayaditya notices her excessive joy! Udayaditya went out to the village to see what was happening, seeing the festive atmosphere on the river bank.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 3/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

এমন কিছুক্ষণ গেল। একজন তীর হইতে জিজ্ঞাসা করিল— “কাহাদের নৌকা গা?” নৌকা হইতে রাজবাটীর ভৃত্যেরা বলিয়া উঠিল।—“কেও? রামমােহন যে? আরে, এস এস!” রামমােহন তাড়াতাড়ি নৌকায় প্রবেশ করিল। নৌকায় একলা বিভা বসিয়া আছে, রামমােহনকে দেখিয়া হর্ষে উচ্ছ্বসিত হইয়া কহিল-—“মােহন।”
</prompt>
<result>
Some time passed like this. Someone from the bank asked, "Whose boat is that?" The servants of the palace replied from the boat, "Who? Rammohan? Oh, come, come!" Rammohan quickly got on the boat. Bibha was sitting alone in the boat, and seeing Rammohan, she exclaimed with joy, "Mohan."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 4/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমােহন—“মা।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan - "Mother."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 5/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমােহন বিভার সেই সরল আনন্দে পরিপূর্ণ, হাসি হাসি মুখখানি অনেক ক্ষণ দেখিয়া ম্লান মুখে কহিল—“মা তুমি আজ আসিলে?”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan was filled with that simple joy, looked at her smiling face for a long time and then said with a gloomy face - "Mother, did you come today?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 6/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা তাড়াতাড়ি কহিল-“হাঁ, মােহন। মহারাজ কি ইহারি মধ্যে সংবাদ পাইয়াছেন? তুই কি আমাকে লইতে আসিয়াছিস্?”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha hurriedly said- "Yes, Mohan. Has the Maharaj received the news in the meantime? Have you come to take me?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 7/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমােহন কহিল—“না মা, অত ব্যস্ত হইও না—আজ থাক্—আর একদিন লইয়া যাইব।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan said, "No mother, don't be in such a hurry—leave it for today—I'll take it another day."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 8/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমোহনের ভাব দেখিয়া বিভা একেবারে মলিন হইয়া গিয়া কহিল —“কেন মোহন—আজ কেন যাইব না!”
</prompt>
<result>
Seeing Rammohan's mood, Bibha became completely disheartened and said, "Why Mohan—why won't I go today!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 9/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমোহন কহিল—“আজ সন্ধ্যা হইয়া গিয়াছে—আজ থাক্, মা।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan said, "It's getting late in the evening today—stay today, mother."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 10/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা নিতান্ত ভীত হইয়া কহিল, “সত্য করিয়া বল মোহন কি হইয়াছে?”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha, utterly frightened, said, "Tell me truly, Mohan, what has happened?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 11/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমোহন থাকিতে পারিল না। আত্মগোপন করা তাহার অভ্যাস নাই! সেইখানেই সে বসিয়া পড়িল—কাঁদিয়া কহিল—“মা জননী, আজ তোমার রাজ্যে তোমার স্থান নাই—তোমার রাজবাটীতে তোমার গৃহ নাই। আজ মহারাজ বিবাহ করিতেছেন।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan couldn't bear it. Hiding was not his habit! He sat down right there—and cried, saying—"Mother, today there is no place for you in your kingdom—no home for you in your palace. Today the Maharaja is getting married."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 12/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভার মুখ একেবারে পাণ্ডুবর্ণ হইয়া গেল। তাহার হাত পা হিম হইয়া গেল! রামমোহন কহিতে লাগিল, “মা, যখন তোর এই অধম সন্তান তোকে ডাকিতে গিয়াছিল, তখন তুই কেন আসিলি না, মা? তখন তুই নিষ্ঠুর পাষাণী হইয়া আমাকে কেন ফিরাইয়া দিলি মা? মহারাজের কাছে আমার যে আর মুখ রহিল না! বুক ফাটিয়া গেল, তবু যে তোর হইয়া একটি কথাও কহিতে পারিলাম না!”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha's face turned completely pale. Her hands and feet became ice-cold! Rammohan started saying, "Mother, when your lowly son went to call you, why didn't you come, Mother? Why did you turn me away like a cruel, heartless woman? I have no face to show the Maharaj now! My heart is breaking, yet I couldn't say a single word because of you!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 13/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা আর চোখে কিছু দেখিতে পাইল না,—মাথা ঘুরিয়া সেইখানে পড়িয়া গেল। রামমোহন তাড়াতাড়ি জল আনিয়া বিভার মুখে চোখে ছিটা দিল। কিছুকণ পরে বিভা উঠিয়া বসিল। এক আঘাতে বিভার সমস্ত জগৎ ভাঙিয়া গেছে। স্বামীর রাজ্যের মধ্যে আসিয়া, রাজধানীর কাছে পৌঁছিয়া, রাজপুরীর দুয়ারে আসিয়া তৃষার্ত্ত-হৃদয় বিভার সমস্ত সুখের আশা মরীচিকার মত মিলাইয়া গেল।
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha could not see anything anymore,—her head spun and she fell down right there. Rammohan quickly brought water and sprinkled it on Bibha's face and eyes. After a while, Bibha sat up. Bibha's entire world had been shattered in one blow. After coming to her husband's kingdom, reaching near the capital, and arriving at the palace gate, thirsty-hearted Bibha's hopes for happiness had vanished like a mirage.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 14/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা আকুল ভাবে কহিল—“মোহন, তিনি যে আমাকে ডাকাইয়া পাঠাইলেন—আমার আসিতে কি বড় বিলম্ব হইয়াছে?
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha said anxiously, "Mohan, he sent for me—was I very late in coming?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 15/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মোহন কহিল, “বিলম্ব হইয়াছে বৈকি।”
</prompt>
<result>
Mohan said, "It's getting late, isn't it?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 16/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা অধীর হইয়া কহিল—“আর কি মার্জ্জনা করিবেন না?”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha said impatiently - "Will you not forgive me anymore?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 17/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

মোহন কহিল—“মার্জ্জনা আর করিলেন কই?”
</prompt>
<result>
Mohan said - "Why didn't you forgive him?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 18/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা কহিল—“মোহন, আমি কেবল একবার তাঁহাকে দেখিতে যাইব।” বলিয়া ঊর্দ্ধশ্বাসে কাঁদিয়া উঠিল।
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha said, "Mohan, I will just go and see him once." Saying this, she burst into tears.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 19/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমোহন চোখ মুছিয়া কহিল—“আজ থাক্ না, মা।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan wiped his eyes and said, "Not today, mother."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 20/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা কহিল—“না মোহন, আমি আজই একবার তাঁহাকে দেখিয়া আসিব।”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha said, "No Mohan, I will go and see him once today."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 21/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমোহন কহিল—“যুবরাজ আগে গ্রাম হইতে ফিরিয়া আসুন।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan said, "Let the Crown Prince return from the village first."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 22/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা কহিল—“না মোহন, আমি এখনি একবার যাই।”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha said, "No Mohan, I'll go once more."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 23/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা মনে করিয়াছিল, উদয়াদিত্য এ সংবাদ শুনিলে অপমানের ভয়ে পাছে না যাইতে দেন।
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha thought that Udayaditya might not let her go out of fear of being humiliated if he heard this news.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 24/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমোহন কহিল—“তবে একখানি শিবিকা আনাই।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan said - "Then bring a palanquin."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 25/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা কহিল—“শিবিকা কেন? আমি কি রাণী যে শিবিকা চাই। আমি একজন সামান্য প্রজার মত, একজন ভিখারিণীর মত যাইব—আমার শিবিকায় কাজ কি?”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha said, "Why a palanquin? Am I a queen to need a palanquin? I will go like an ordinary subject, like a beggar woman—what use do I have for a palanquin?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 26/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমোহন কহিল—“আমার প্রাণ থাকিতে আমি তাহা দেখিতে পারিব না।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan said, "As long as I am alive, I will not allow that to happen."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 27/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা কাতর স্বরে কহিল—“মোহন, তোর পায়ে পড়ি আমাকে আর বাধা দিস্ নে—বিলম্ব হইয়া যাইতেছে!”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha said in a pleading voice, "Mohan, I beg you, don't stop me anymore—I'm getting late!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 28/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমোহন ব্যথিত হৃদয়ে কহিল—“আচ্ছা মা, তাহাই হউক্।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan said with a pained heart, "Alright mother, so be it."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 29/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা সামান্য রমণীর বেশে নৌকা হইতে বাহির হইল। নৌকার ভৃত্যেরা আসিয়া কহিল—“এ কি মা, এমন করিয়া এ বেশে কোথাও যাও।”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha got out of the boat disguised as a young woman. The boat's servants came and said, "What is this, mother? Why are you going somewhere dressed like this?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 30/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমোহন কহিল—“এ ত মায়েরই রাজ্য, যেখানে ইচ্ছা সেইখানেই যাইতে পারেন!”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan said - "This is mother's kingdom, she can go wherever she wants!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 36] 31/31</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভৃত্যেরা আপত্তি করিতে লাগিল, রামমোহন তাহাদের ভাগাইয়া দিল।
</prompt>
<result>
The servants started to object, Rammohan pushed them aside.
</result>
</query>
</queries>
