<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<queries count="16">
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 1/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

## সপ্তত্রিংশ পরিচ্ছেদ।
</prompt>
<result>
## Chapter 37
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 2/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

চারিদিকে লােক জন, চারিদিকেই ভিড়। আগে হইলে বিভা সঙ্কোচে মরিয়া যাইত, আজ কিছুই যেন তাহার চোখে পড়িতেছে না। যাহা কিছু দেখিতেছে সমস্তই যেন বিভার মিথ্যা বলিয়া মনে হইতেছে। চারিদিকে যেন একটা কোলাহলময় স্বপ্নের ঘেঁসাঘেঁসি—কিছুই যেন কিছু নয়। চারিদিকে একটা ভিড় চোখে পড়িতেছে এই পর্য্যন্ত, চারিদিক হইতে একটা কোলাহল শােনা যাইতেছে এই পর্য্যন্ত, তাহার যেন একটা কোন অর্থ নাই।
</prompt>
<result>
There were people and crowd all around. Earlier, Bibha would have died of embarrassment, but today nothing seemed to catch her eye. Whatever she saw, it all seemed like a lie to Bibha. All around her, there was a cacophony of a dream—nothing seemed to be anything. All she could see was a crowd, all she could hear was a commotion, but it all seemed meaningless to her.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 3/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ভিড়ের মধ্য দিয়া রাজপুরীর দ্বারের নিকট আসিতেই একজন দ্বারী সহসা বিভার হাত ধরিয়া বিভাকে নিবারণ করিল—তখন সহসা বিভা এক মুহূর্ত্তে বাহ্য জগতের মধ্যে আসিয়া পড়িল—চারিদিক দেখিতে পাইল লজ্জায় মরিয়া গেল। তাহার ঘােমটা খুলিয়া গিয়াছিল, তাড়াতাড়ি মাথার ঘােমটা তুলিয়া দিল। রামমােহন আগে আগে যাইতেছিল, সে পশ্চাৎ ফিরিয়া দ্বারীর প্রতি চোখ পাকাইয়া দাঁড়াইল—অদূরে ফর্ণাণ্ডিজ ছিল, সে আসিয়া দ্বারীকে ধরিয়া বিলক্ষণ শাসন করিল। বিভা প্রাসাদে প্রবেশ করিল। অন্যান্য দাসদাসীর ন্যায় বিভা প্রাসাদে প্রবেশ করিল—কেহ তাহাকে সমাদর করিল না!
</prompt>
<result>
As she was coming near the entrance of the palace through the crowd, a gatekeeper suddenly caught hold of Bibha's hand and stopped her—at that moment Bibha suddenly came back to reality—she looked around and felt ashamed. Her veil had come off, she quickly pulled her veil over her head. Rammohan was walking ahead, he turned back and glared at the gatekeeper—Fernandez was nearby, he came and scolded the gatekeeper. Bibha entered the palace. Bibha entered the palace like any other maidservant—no one paid any attention to her!
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 4/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

ঘরে কেবল রাজা ও রমাই ভাঁড় বসিয়াছিলেন। বিভা গৃহে প্রবেশ করিয়া রাজার মুখের দিকে চাহিয়াই রাজার পায়ের কাছে ভূমিতে পড়িয়া গেল। রাজা শশব্যস্ত হইয়া দাঁড়াইয়া জিজ্ঞাসা করিলেন, “কে তুই? ভিখারিণী—ভিক্ষা চাহিতে আসিয়াছিস্?”
</prompt>
<result>
Only the king and the jester, Ramai Bhaand, were sitting in the room. Bibha entered the room, looked at the king's face, and fell to the ground at the king's feet. The king stood up in surprise and asked, "Who are you? A beggar—have you come to beg?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 5/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা নত-মুখ তুলিয়া অশ্রুপূর্ণ নেত্রে রাজার মুখের দিকে চাহিয়া কহিল, “না মহারাজ, আমার সর্ব্বস্ব দান করিতে আসিয়াছি। আমি তােমাকে পরের হাতে সমর্পণ করিয়া বিদায় লইতে আসিয়াছি।”
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha raised her tearful face and looked at the king and said, "No, Your Majesty, I have come to give you everything I have. I have come to bid you farewell by surrendering you into someone else's hands."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 6/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমােহন থাকিতে পারিল না, কাছে আসিয়া কহিল—“মহারাজ, আপনার মহিষী—যশােহরের রাজকুমারী।”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan could not stay away, he came near and said - "Maharaj, your queen - the princess of Jashore."
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 7/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

সহসা রামচন্দ্র রায়ের প্রাণ যেন কেমন চম্‌কিয়া উঠিল—কিন্তু তৎক্ষণাৎ রমাই ভাঁড় হাসিয়া রাজার দিকে কটাক্ষ করিয়া কঠোর-কণ্ঠে কহিল, “কেন এখন কি আর দাদাকে মনে ধরে না নাকি?”
</prompt>
<result>
Suddenly Ramchandra Roy's soul seemed to be startled—but immediately the jester Ramai laughed and glancing at the king said in a harsh voice, "Why, don't you like your elder brother any more?"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 8/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামচন্দ্ররায়ের হৃদয়ে করুণার আভাস জাগিয়া উঠিয়াছিল, তথাপি রমাইয়ের কথায় তিনি নিষ্ঠুর হাস্য করিয়া উঠিলেন— তিনি ভাবিলেন—বিভাকে এখন মমতা দেখাইলে পাছে উপহাসাস্পদ হইতে হয়।
</prompt>
<result>
Ramchandra Ray's heart was filled with compassion, yet he laughed cruelly at Ramai's words—he thought—if he showed affection to Bibha now, he might become an object of ridicule.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 9/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভার মাথায় একেবারে সহস্র বজ্রাঘাত হইল—সে লজ্জায় একেবারে মরিয়া গেল—চোখ বুজিয়া মনে মনে কহিল—মা গাে, বসুন্ধরা, তুমি দ্বিধা হও! কাতর হইয়া চারিদিকে চাহিল—রামমােহনের মুখের দিকে একবার অসহায় দৃষ্টিতে চাহিয়া দেখিল!
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha felt as if a thousand thunderbolts had struck her head at once—she was utterly mortified—she closed her eyes and said in her mind—Oh Mother Earth, please open up and swallow me! She looked around in panic—she looked at Rammohan's face with helpless eyes!
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 10/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমােহন ছুটিয়া আসিয়া সবলে রমাই ভাঁড়ের ঘাড় টিপিয়া ধরিয়া তাহাকে ঘর হইতে বাহির করিয়া দিল।
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan came running and forcefully grabbed hold of Romai the buffoon's neck and threw him out of the house.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 11/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রাজা ক্রুদ্ধ হইয়া কহিলেন—“রামমােহন, তুই আমার সম্মুখে বেয়াদবি করিস্!”
</prompt>
<result>
The king became angry and said, "Rammohan, you are being impertinent in front of me!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 12/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রামমােহন কাঁপিতে কাঁপিতে কহিল—“মহারাজ, আমি বেয়াদবি করিলাম! তােমার মহিষীকে আমার মাঠাকরুণকে বেটা অপমান করিল—উহার হইয়াছে কি, আমি উহার মাথা মুড়াইয়া ঘােল ঢালিয়া সহর হইতে বাহির করিয়া দিব, তবে আমার নাম রামমােহন!”
</prompt>
<result>
Rammohan said with a trembling voice, "Your Majesty, I have committed a grave offense! Your queen insulted my mother, I will shave her head, pour ashes on it, and banish her from the city, only then my name will be Rammohan!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 13/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

রাজা রামমােহনকে, ধমক দিয়া কহিলেন—“কে আমার মহিষী? আমি উহাকে চিনি না!”
</prompt>
<result>
He threatened Raja Rammohan and said, "Who is my queen? I don't know her!"
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 14/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভার মুখ নীল হইয়া গেল, সে মুখে আঁচল চাপিয়া ধরিল, থর থর করিয়া তাহার সর্ব্বাঙ্গ কাঁপিতে লাগিল, ও অবশেষে কাঁপিতে কাঁপিতে বিভা মূর্চ্ছিতা হইয়া ভূমিতে পড়িল। তখন রামমােহন যােড়হস্তে রাজাকে কহিল—“মহারাজ, আজ চার পুরুষে তােমার বংশে আমরা চাকরী করিয়া আসিতেছি। বাল্যকাল হইতে তােমাকে পালন করিয়াছি। আজ তুমি আমার মাঠাক্‌রুণকে অপমান করিলে, তােমার রাজ্য-লক্ষ্মীকে দূর করিয়া দিলে—আজ আমিও তােমার চাকরী ছাড়িয়া দিয়া চলিলাম—আমার মাঠাক্‌রুণের সেবা করিয়া জীবন কাটাইব। ভিক্ষা করিয়া খাইব তবুও এ রাজবাটির ছায়া মাড়াইব না।” বলিয়া রামমােহন রাজাকে প্রণাম করিল ও বিভাকে কহিল—“আয় মা, আয়! এখান হইতে শীঘ্র চলিয়া আয়! আর এক মুহূর্ত্তও এখানে থাকা নয়।” বলিয়া বিভাকে ধরিয়া তুলিয়া আনিল। দ্বারের নিকট অনেকগুলি শিবিকা ছিল, তাহার মধ্যে একটিতে হতজ্ঞান অবসন্ন বিভাকে তুলিয়া, নৌকায় ফিরিয়া আসিল।
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha's face turned pale, she covered her face with her veil, her whole body started trembling, and finally, trembling and trembling, Bibha fainted and fell to the ground. Then Rammohan folded his hands and said to the king, "Your Majesty, for four generations, we have been serving your dynasty. We have been taking care of you since your childhood. Today, you have insulted my mistress, you have driven away the goddess of fortune of your kingdom - today I also quit your service and leave - I will serve my mistress and spend my life. I will beg and eat, but I will not cross the shadow of this palace." Saying this, Rammohan bowed to the king and said to Bibha, "Come on mother, come on! Leave this place quickly! Don't stay here for a moment longer." Saying this, he picked up Bibha and brought her. There were many palanquins near the door, he lifted the unconscious and exhausted Bibha into one of them and returned to the boat.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 15/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

বিভা উদয়াদিত্যের সহিত কাশী চলিয়া গেল। সেই খানে দান, ধ্যান, দেবসেবা ও তাহার ভ্রাতার সেবায় জীবন কাটাইতে লাগিল। রামমােহন যতদিন বাঁচিয়া ছিল, তাহাদের সঙ্গে ছিল। সীতারামও সপরিবারে কাশীতে আসিয়া উদয়াদিত্যের আশ্রয় লইল।
</prompt>
<result>
Bibha went to Kashi with Udayaditya. There she spent her life in charity, meditation, worshiping deities, and serving her brother. Rammohan was with them as long as he lived. Sitaram also came to Kashi with his family and took shelter with Udayaditya.
</result>
</query>
<query>
<info>[Chapter 37] 16/16</info>
<prompt>
Please translate each line literally into English.

চন্দ্রদ্বীপের যে হাটের সম্মুখে বিভার নৌকা লাগিয়াছিল, অদ্যাপি তাহার নাম রহিয়াছে—“বৌ-ঠাকুরাণীর হাট।”
</prompt>
<result>
The market in Chandradwip in front of which Bibha's boat had anchored, is still known as "Bou-Thakurani'r Haat" (Bou-Thakurani's Market).
</result>
</query>
</queries>
